<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Answers for the Earl of Lauderdale, to a printed paper, (entituled, The case of John Swinton, in relation to his fathers forefaulture) and to the pretended reasons of reduction of the said forfaulture, alledged to be now depending before the Parliament.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1690</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 112 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B01414</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3467</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R170333</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">53981599</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 53981599</idno>
            <idno type="VID">180098</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B01414)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 180098)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2813:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Answers for the Earl of Lauderdale, to a printed paper, (entituled, The case of John Swinton, in relation to his fathers forefaulture) and to the pretended reasons of reduction of the said forfaulture, alledged to be now depending before the Parliament.</title>
                  <author>Lauderdale, Charles Maitland, Earl of, d. 1691.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[37] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by the heir of Andrew Anderson,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1690.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Initial letter.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the National Library of Scotland.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Swinton, John, 1621?-1679.</term>
               <term>Lauderdale, John Maitland, --  Duke of, 1616-1682.</term>
               <term>Forfeiture --  Scotland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Korey Jackson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Korey Jackson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:180098:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:180098:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ANSWERS FOR THE EARL of LAUDERDALE, TO A PRINTED PAPER, (Entituled, The Caſe of JOHN SWINTON, <hi>In relation to his Fathers Forefaulture) and to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Reaſons of Reduction of the ſaid Forfaulture, Alledged to be now depending before the Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> Printed by the Heir of <hi>Andrew Anderſon;</hi> 1690.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:180098:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:180098:2"/>
            <head>Anſwers for the Earl of <hi>Lauderdale,</hi> to a Printed Paper (Entituled, The Caſe of <hi>John Swinton,</hi> in relation to his Fathers Forfaulture) and to the pretended Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of Reduction of the ſaid Forfaulture, Alledged to be now depending before the Parliament.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE deceaſt <hi>John Swinton,</hi> being a Perſon of a conſiderable Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt and Truſt in the Kingdom of <hi>Scotland,</hi> in <hi>Anno</hi> 1651. U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the Invaſion of <hi>Cromwel,</hi> and the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Rebels, <hi>Swinton</hi> did deſert his Soveraign, and Native Countrey, and abandoned his Charge in the Army; and did joyn and aſſociat himſelf with the Uſurper <hi>Cromwell;</hi> for which he and ſome other Traitors were Cited before the Parliament at <hi>Perth;</hi> and the matter being remitted by the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament to the Committee of Eſtates; and His late Majeſty King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second being preſent in the Committee; and the matter being both notourly known, as alſo ſufficiently proven, <hi>John Swinton</hi> was Forefault in <hi>anno</hi> 1651. for deſerting his Charge in the Army, and joyning with <hi>Cromwel:</hi> Thereafter <hi>John Swinton</hi> marched with <hi>Cromwel</hi> to <hi>Worcester,</hi> and did actually appear in Arms againſt his Soveraign in Perſon, when the Royal Family, and his Native Countrey, were at the laſt and outmoſt extremity, where the late Duke of <hi>Lauderdale,</hi> being taken Priſoner in defence of his Soveraigns Right, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of his native Countrey from ſlavery, was thereafter detained three years cloſs Priſoner in the Tower of <hi>London,</hi> expecting every hour the ſtroak of the Executioner; and was kept other three years in a Vault at <hi>Portland</hi>-Caſtle, and being tranſported thence to <hi>Windſor</hi>-Caſtle, he was likewiſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained Priſoner there other three years: And being Forfeited for his Loyalty by thoſe Regicides, <hi>John Swinton</hi> did improve his Intereſt and Power he had with the Uſurper <hi>Cromwell,</hi> (being his great Minion and Truſtee, being no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minat by him to be a Lord both of Council, Exchequer and Seſſion) to ſo baſe and ungenerous ends, that he did perſecute thoſe who had faithfully ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hered to their Soveraign and Native Countrey, in their diſtreſs, and did pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure in his own Favours a Gift of the Duke of <hi>Lauderdale</hi>'s Forfaulture, and thereby did poſſeſs a conſiderable part of his Eſtate, to the value of one thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Pounds <hi>Sterling per annum,</hi> for the ſpace of more than 8 years; the reſt of the Duke's Eſtate being poſſeſſed by as notorious Traitors as himſelf, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring all which time, the Duke of <hi>Lauderdale</hi>'s Lady and Daughter, were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to ſuch ſtraits and neceſſities, that they had not Bread to eat, the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:180098:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
unjuſt Invaders of his Eſtate, neither allowing him any thing out of the ſame, to maintain himſelf and his Family, nor yet interpoſing with the Uſurper for an allowance out of the Publick: In which condition the Duke lived, till it pleaſed God to extricate him out of theſe ſtraits and difficulties, by the happy Reſtauration of his Native Soveraign King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, in <hi>anno</hi> 1660.</p>
            <p>In <hi>anno</hi> 1661. <hi>John Swinton</hi> was ſent down Priſoner from <hi>London,</hi> to be Judged by the Parliament of <hi>Scotland;</hi> and being conveened before the Parliament, His <hi>Majeſties</hi> Advocat did inſiſt againſt him, not only upon the former Sentence, and Doom of Forfaulture paſt againſt him in <hi>anno</hi> 1651. And that the ſamine might be put to further Execution, but likewiſe exhibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a new Inditement againſt him, upon ſeveral new additional Articles of Treaſon, and particularly upon his going along with the Rebels to, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in Arms at the Fight of <hi>Worceſter</hi> againſt his Soveraign in perſon: And <hi>John Swinton</hi> having appeared ſeveral times in the Pannel, he not only <hi>viva voce</hi> did acknowledge, but by Defences Written and Subſcribed with his own Hand, given in to the Parliament, he confeſſed his being in Arms at <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſter</hi> with the Uſurper <hi>Cromwel</hi> againſt his Soveraign, but did plead the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite of the Act of Indemnity in <hi>England,</hi> which did not at all concern <hi>Scots<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> whereupon the Parliament in <hi>anno</hi> 1661, did not only Ratifie and Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove the former Doom and Sentence of Forfaulture pronounced againſt the ſaid <hi>John Swinton,</hi> by the Committee of Eſtates in <hi>anno</hi> 1651, but alſo for the additional Crimes contained in the new Inditement acknowledged by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, both <hi>viva voce</hi> before the Parliament, and by the Written and Subſcrib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Defences <hi>Swinton</hi> was again Forfaulted: And in the next Seſſion of that ſame Parliament, the Doom of Forfaulture againſt <hi>Swinton</hi> is mentioned and related in the Act of Indemnity, and he and ſome others are expreſly excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from the Indemnity, as ſtanding Forfault by that ſame Parliament.</p>
            <p>King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second was graciouſly pleaſed to gift and beſtow <hi>Swinton</hi>'s Forfaulture to the late Duke of <hi>Lauderdale,</hi> not only in conſideration of his faithful Services, and great Sufferings, but particularly becauſe <hi>John Swinton</hi> had taken a Gift from the Uſurpers, of a conſiderable part of the Duke of <hi>Lauderdale</hi>'s Eſtate: So that there was never any Forfaulture upon more juſt and important Crimes, nor did ever any Prince Gift a Forfaulture upon more reaſonable and equitable conſiderations. Nevertheleſs after the Duke of <hi>Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derdale</hi>'s deceaſe, in <hi>anno</hi> 1682, when his Family and Repreſentatives were in very hard circumſtances, <hi>Swinton</hi>'s Son did impetrat and procure from the late King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, upon moſt falſe and diſingenuous repreſentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, a Commiſſion for enquiring into the Method and Procedure, and the Warrands upon Record of <hi>Swinton</hi>'s Forfaulture: and there being a multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of frivolous Objections offered by <hi>Swinton</hi>'s Son, and full Anſwers there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, by the Earl of <hi>Lauderdale,</hi> and the Creditors of the deceaſt Duke of <hi>Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derdale:</hi> And both Parties being heard <hi>viva voce</hi> before that Commiſſion, the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:180098:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Commiſſioners were fully ſatisfied, that nothing of moment was inſtructed, and that the Crimes for which <hi>Swinton</hi> was Forfeited at <hi>Perth, viz.</hi> his deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting his Charge in the Army, and joyning with the Rebel <hi>Cromwel,</hi> and his being thereafter in Arms at <hi>Worceſter,</hi> for which he was again Forfeited in the Parliament, 1661. was not only true and incontroverted, but acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged by <hi>Swinton</hi> himſelf, in his Anſwers given in to his Inditement, which were Written and Subſcribed with his own Hand, as ſaid is: So that if there had been any Informality in the Proceſſes of Forfeiture, as there were none; yet theſe Informalities could have no effect, and ought not to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded: Eſpecially ſeing by the 135 <hi>Act, Parl.</hi> 8. K. Ja. the 6. It is Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted, that no Forfeiture for Treaſon againſt the King, and His Eſtates, ſhall be Reduced for any pretended Cauſe of Nullity, that may be Alledged to have been in the Proceſs, except the Crime be either Remitted by His Majeſty, or that it could be purged and acquit by a Tryal. Whereupon the Commiſſion was deſerted.</p>
            <p>Thereafter the ſaid <hi>John Swinton</hi>'s Son and his Relations, being conſcious to themſelves, that they could not prevail to Reduce the foreſaids two De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creets of Forfeiture, pronounced againſt his deceaſt Father, the Crimes for which he was Forfeit being both notour and proven, and acknowledged by himſelf, they did fall upon another Contrivance, which was in <hi>anno</hi> 1685, or 1686. to procure an Rehabilitation to <hi>Swinton</hi>'s Children, with a Remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Crime, thinking thereby, and by the intereſt with the Quakers, and others who had then Influence at Court, that they would lay a force upon the Earl of <hi>Lauderdale,</hi> either to Tranſact with the ſaid <hi>John Swinton</hi> for the Eſtate of <hi>Swinton,</hi> or if he refuſed to do the ſame, they would procure a Recommendation to the next Parliament, to Reduce the Forfeitures upon the former frivolous Objections, and pretended Nullities offered before the Commiſſion: But the Tenor of the Rehabilitation running upon theſe ſame falſe Grounds and Suggeſtions, which were inſinuat to King <hi>Charles</hi> the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, when the Commiſſion was obtained in <hi>anno</hi> 1682. and which being objected againſt by the Lord <hi>Maitland,</hi> then at Court, the Letter of Rehabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation in favours of <hi>Swinton</hi>'s Children, was refuſed.</p>
            <p>This being a ſhort and true Account of the matter of Fact in relation to the Forfeitures of <hi>Swinton,</hi> and the Gift thereof in Favours of the late Duke of <hi>Lauderdale,</hi> and the Contrivances that have been fallen upon of late to quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel the ſame: A Paper lately came out in Print, (<hi>Intituled the Caſe of</hi> John Swinton <hi>of</hi> Swinton, in relation to his Fathers Forfeiture, with the Reaſons of Reduction of the ſaid Forfeiture) ſhall be made appear to any indifferent perſon to be Diſingenious, Falſe, Calumnious, and inconſiſtent with the Laws of this, and all other Nations, both from what has been ſaid before, and what ſhall be hereafter ſaid in the particular Anſwers to the Reaſons of Reduction.</p>
            <p>It is repreſented in the ſaid Paper, that the Duke of <hi>Lauderdale</hi> after the Reſtauration of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, firſt entered into the Poſſeſſion, and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:180098:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
then obtained a Gift of the Deceaſt <hi>Swinton</hi>'s Eſtate, upon pretence of his being Forfeited by the Committee of Eſtates, in <hi>anno</hi> 1651. for his being with the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> albeit there was nothing ever could be made appear to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince that there was ever any ſuch Forfeiture againſt <hi>Swinton</hi> in the year 1651. But the pretended Extract of a Decreet in abſence, elicite from an Under Clerk ten years after, of which there was never the leaſt Warrand upon Record. And as to the Forfeiture in the year 1661. there was only a Proceſs intented, which never came the length of a Sentence: And <hi>Swin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> having objected it to the Duke of <hi>Lauderdale,</hi> in the latter end of the year 1673. There were Methods taken in <hi>January</hi> 1674. for making up of the Minuts, as if a Sentence of Forfeiture had followed upon the Proceſs, and a Decreet extracted upon the ſame, 13, or 14 years after the intended Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, and Sir <hi>Archibald Primeroſe,</hi> who was then Clerk Regiſter, dealt firſt with the Earl of <hi>Crafurd</hi> to ſign the ſaid Minuts, albeit 13 years after that Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, at leaſt that Seſſion of Parliament was no more in being, and then cauſed application to be made in behalf of the Duke of <hi>Lawderdale,</hi> to the Lords of Seſſion, to give their Warrant for Extracting, what he was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcious to himſelf was ſo unwarrantably done: And that the Earl of <hi>Crafurd</hi> had declared under his hand, by a Letter left with his Daughter, Lady <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len Sinclair,</hi> how he was prevailed with by the ſaid Sir <hi>Archibald Primroſe,</hi> to ſo unjuſtifiable a practice, and which Letter is ſet down at length in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Paper; and that the Duke of <hi>Lauderdale</hi> notwithſtanding of his great power, durſt not adventure, albeit that he knew his Title to that Eſtate, to be defective, to put a Crime ſo calumnious, as was charged upon the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſt <hi>John Swinton,</hi> to the Tryal of a Parliament, knowing that he would have been able to have Cleared himſelf: And that the Letter written by the Earl of <hi>Crafurd,</hi> having been ſhown to the King, he did grant a Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to make inquiry in the whole procedor, concerning <hi>Swinton's</hi> Forfeiture, and to inſpect the Records of Parliament, in relation to the ſame, and to make Report thereof to His Majeſty. And the Records of Parliament being inſpected, there was nothing found, that related to any pretended Decreet of Forfeiture againſt <hi>Swinton,</hi> in the Parliament 1651. And as to the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment 1661. all that was found, did appear from the Records of Parliament to be falſe. But this Earl of <hi>Lauderdale,</hi> had that influence, upon thoſe, to whom the Commiſſion was direct, as rendered the ſame ineffectual.</p>
            <p>This being the ſum of <hi>John Swinton</hi>'s Caſe, as he's pleaſed to term it; It is An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered thereto, 1<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. That it is moſt falſe and calumnious, that the Duke of <hi>Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derdale</hi> did enter to the poſſeſſion of the Eſtate of <hi>Swinton,</hi> before he obtained the Gift of Forfeiture: For the deceas'd <hi>John Swinton</hi> being Forfeited by the Committee of Eſtates, in <hi>anno</hi> 1651. who had power from the Parliament, then ſitting at <hi>Perth,</hi> to diſcuſs the relevancy, and probation of the Inditement, raiſed againſt the ſaid deceaſt <hi>John Swinton</hi> and others, and to decide and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine therein, as fully in all reſpects, as the Parliament ſitting in <hi>pleno e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> |ſeſſu,</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:180098:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
might have done: After the King's Reſtauration, that ſame Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee being appointed by the King to meet in <hi>anno</hi> 1660. to mannage the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick concerns of the Kingdom, until a Parliament was called, they amongſt other things, did Sequeſtrat the ſaid <hi>John Swinton's</hi> Eſtate, whom they knew they had Forfeited in <hi>anno</hi> 1651. and did appoint <hi>George Hume</hi> of <hi>Kaimes,</hi> to intromet with the Rent of the ſaid Eſtate, and to be comptable to the King, or Lords of Theſaury. And the Duke of <hi>Lauderdale</hi> did not intromet with a ſix pence thereof, until the <hi>Martinmaſs</hi> 1661. which was long after, both the laſt Sentence of Forfeiture, and his Gift thereof from his Majeſty. 2<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. As to the Decreet of Forfeiture in <hi>anno</hi> 1651. Altho the Warrands thereof were loſt, with ſeveral other publick Records coming down from <hi>London</hi> in <hi>anno</hi> 1660. yet the Extract thereof muſt make as much Faith, as if the War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants thereof were yet extant, ſeing it is notourly known, that the Lords of Seſſion ſuſtains all Extracts out of the Regiſters of theſe years 1648, 49, 50, and 51. and refuſes to grant Certifications againſt any Writs Regiſtrat theſe years, becauſe the Warrants of the Regiſters of theſe years were loſt: But that which puts the truth and verity of this Decreet, beyond all queſtion is this, that Lieutenant <hi>Govan</hi> who was Forfeited at that ſame time with <hi>John Swinton,</hi> and contained in the ſame Decreet with him, was put to death by Order of the Parliament, in <hi>anno</hi> 1661. by vertue of the firſt Sentence in <hi>anno</hi> 1651; as is evident by the laſt Minuts upon the Margin of that De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creet, <hi>anno</hi> 1651. Ordaining the Sentence of Death to be execute againſt him, conform to the ſaid Decreet; and which Minuts are Subſcribed by the then Preſident of the Parliament, 1661. So that to Redargue the Faith and Verity of that Decreet of Forfeiture, were to accuſe the Parliament of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt Injuſtice, and lay an Imputation upon the Parliament, of putting a Man to death upon a falſe Decreet, which the meaneſt Judicature in <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> could not be guilty of, far leſs the Supreme Judicature of the Nation: and it is obvious to any man's ſenſe, that if this Decreet had been falſe, Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant <hi>Govan</hi> when he was called before the Parliament, and received the Order, and Sentence of Death, would have reclaimed againſt the Faith and Verity of that Decreet; ſo that the Parliaments Approbation of this Decreet of Forfeiture, by executing of <hi>Govan,</hi> and his not reclaiming againſt the ſame, and the Parliaments again approving thereof in the laſt Sentence of Forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture againſt <hi>Swinton,</hi> in <hi>anno</hi> 1661. are unanſwerable Documents of the Verity and Faith of the ſaid Decreet.</p>
            <p n="3">3<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. For aſtructing the Verity of the Decreet of Forfeiture in <hi>anno</hi> 1661. there needs no more be ſaid, but that the Liſt of the Unprinted Acts of the firſt Seſſion of the Parliament, <hi>anno</hi> 1661. contains both the Decreet of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiture againſt <hi>John Swinton,</hi> and he Ratification in favours of the late Duke of <hi>Lauderdale,</hi> of the Gift of <hi>Swinton's</hi> Forfeiture: And in the Act of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnity, which was paſt in the ſecond Seſſion of that ſame Parliament, the Decreet of Forfeiture againſt <hi>John Swinton,</hi> is particularly excepted there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>from,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:180098:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
which beyond all queſtion doth adminiculat and aſtruct the Verity of the ſaid Sentence and Doom of Forfeiture, and that the ſame was made up after the year 1673. appears evidently to be falſe, becauſe the perſon who Scrolled that Decreet of Forfeiture, whoſe name was <hi>Brown,</hi> was put out of <hi>Hayſtoun's</hi> Service and Writing-Chamber in <hi>anno</hi> 1663, and was dead before the year 1670. And the Regiſters of the Decreets of Forfeiture were all Written in one Book by <hi>David Plenderleith,</hi> before the year 1669. and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered in to the Regiſter, and amongſt which is inſert the ſame Sentence of Forfeiture againſt <hi>Swinton,</hi> ſo that the falſeneſs of that aſſertion is evident, that the Parliament 1661. did not proceed to a Sentence upon that Proceſs, raiſed againſt <hi>Swinton,</hi> and that there were never Decreets Extracted till the year 1674. and Sir <hi>Archibald Primroſe</hi> was known to be a perſon of ſuch In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity, and ſo Cautious in all his Actings, that although he be loaded by <hi>John Swinton</hi> with ſiniſtrous and indirect Methods, in making up of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutes of the ſaid Decreet, and procuring a Warrant for Extracting the ſame, not ſparing his Reputation now after his death, to attain his unjuſt ends, which he durſt not in the leaſt adventure upon while he was alive: Yet by what has been ſaid, and by the following Anſwers to <hi>John Swinton</hi>'s preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Reaſons of Reduction, it ſhall be made evident and clear, he did nothing in this Affair, but what he was warranted both from the Records of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and Laws of the Kingdom. 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. As to that pretence, that it was thought ſtrange that the Duke of <hi>Lauderdale,</hi> being a man of ſuch power, durſt not adventure to put a Crime ſo Calumniouſly Charged upon <hi>John Swinton,</hi> to the Tryal of a Parliament. It is Anſwered, It is thought more ſtrange, that <hi>John Swinton</hi> being innocent of theſe Crimes, as is pretended in the ſaid Paper, for which he was Indited and Convict, both by the Committee of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, 1651. and Parliament 1661. ſhould have ſuffered the Duke of <hi>Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derdale</hi> to poſſeſs his Eſtate during his Life, who died but in <hi>anno</hi> 1679. and did never make application either to the Parliament, 1661. or to any other Parliament that was keeped ſince, for Redreſſing that pretended In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury that he received by the Duke of <hi>Lauderdale's</hi> pretended unjuſt poſſeſſion of his Eſtate, or for Vindicating himſelf of thoſe notorious Crimes whereof he was Indited and Convict: And if there was no Sentence of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiture pronounced againſt the ſaid deceaſed <hi>John Swinton,</hi> how came this <hi>John Swinton</hi> to Addreſs to, and Imploy his Intereſt with the Quakers and others in <hi>England,</hi> who had influence on His Majeſty for a Commiſſion, for inquiring into the ſaid Forfeiture, and procedor thereof; and when this could take no effect, for a Rehabilitation to the deceaſt <hi>John Swinton's</hi> Children, and for a Remiſſion of the Crime to the deceaſt <hi>John Swinton</hi> himſelf; for if there was no Decreet of Forfeiture againſt <hi>John Swinton,</hi> there needed no Commiſſion for inquiring thereunto, neither was it neceſſary to have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired a Rehabilitation in favours of his Children; and if he was not guilty of Treaſon, there was no need of a Remiſſion: And how came the deceaſt
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:180098:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>John Swinton</hi> in his Speech before the Parliament, 1661. to endeavour to extenuat his Guilt, by pretending that the Ambition of his younger years ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving entred him too early into publick Imployment, did make him Act theſe things, which if they were to do, he would rather with the one hand ſtrike off the other, than be guilty of them; and that he ſpoke this, can be made appear by many Witneſſes, yet alive: And if he had been as innocent of the Crimes for which he was Forfeited, as is pretended by his Son's Paper, would he have uſed ſuch an expreſſion as this? which clears, that he was not only guilty of the Crimes, but likewiſe that he was ſenſible of his Fault. But the truth is, <hi>John Swinton</hi> does ſometime run to one Shift, and ſometime to another, as he thinks will help forward his preſent Deſign, and notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of his pretended ſimplicity, he reſolves <hi>calumniari audacter ut aliquid adhereat.</hi> 5<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. As to that Alledgance, that the Earl of <hi>Lauderdale</hi> had ſuch In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence upon theſe to whom the Commiſſion was direct in <hi>anno</hi> 1682, as ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred the proſecution thereof ineffectual. It is Anſwered, That this is very ſuitable to the reſt of his Alledgances, and is a groſs Reflection upon thoſe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minat in the Commiſſion, ſome of them being as eminent perſons, and of as known Integrity as is in the Kingdom: and the Alledgance is moſt Calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious, for as the Commiſſion was impetrat and obtained by <hi>John Swinton,</hi> and his Friends their importunity; ſo its very notour, that the Commiſſioners named in the ſaid Commiſſion, were <hi>John Swinton</hi>'s very good Friends for the moſt part, and whom by his Power and Influence at Court for the time he procured moſt of them ſo to be named and appointed, and that the World may judge how the Earl of <hi>Lauderdale</hi> was ſtated with the moſt part of the Commiſſioners, their Names are ſubjoyned at the end of thir Anſwers.</p>
            <p>This being in ſhort the Anſwer to <hi>John Swinton</hi>'s Caſe, as it is ſtated before his pretended Reaſons of Reduction, except to the deceaſt Earl of <hi>Crafurd</hi>'s Letter, (which will come in more properly afterwards in the Anſwer to the Objection againſt the Minuts.) The next thing that falls in to be conſidered, are his pretended Reaſons of Reduction.</p>
            <p>To the firſt Reaſon whereof being againſt the Decreet of the Committee of Eſtates in <hi>anno</hi> 1651, and bearing, that it is a Decreet in Abſence, not ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed by the Clerk Regiſter for the time, but by Mr. <hi>Thomas Henderſon</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Clerk to that Committee, from whom an Extract was elicit in <hi>anno</hi> 1661, ten years thereafter, and whereof there is no Warrant extant in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords of Parliament.</p>
            <p>It is Anſwered, 1<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. That it is notourly known that Mr. <hi>Thomas Henderſon</hi> who Subſcribes the Extract of the Decreet of Forfeiture, pronounced by the Committee of Eſtates in <hi>anno</hi> 1651, to whom the Parliament had remitted theſe Proceſſes of Forfeitures, was Clerk to the ſaid Committee of Eſtates, and the Extract of the Decreet bears, not only the Forfeiture of <hi>John Swinton,</hi> but
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:180098:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
of ſeveral other perſons, and amongſt the reſt Lieutenant <hi>Govan,</hi> who upon the ſame Decreet was Execute, as appears by the Minuts in <hi>anno</hi> 1661 upon the Margine thereof, the laſt Minut whereof is ordaining that Decreet of Forfeiture to be put to further execution againſt <hi>Govan,</hi> and is Subſcribed by the Preſident of the Parliament 1661, and the Sentence of Death was accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly execute againſt him thereupon, though his Crimes were far leſs ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious and notour than theſe of <hi>John Swinton</hi>'s; and Clerks to Committees of Eſtates, or Criminal Courts, or any of the Regiſters Deputs, do grant au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thentick and valid Extracts, although not ſubſcribed by the Clerk Regiſter; and it is a meer Calumny that the Extract was elicit from Mr. <hi>Thomas Hender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> in the year 1661, and it is an intollerable imputation and reflection upon the Parliament, to ſay, that they would upon the ſame Extract have ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Govan</hi> to be Execute, and ratified and approven the Forfeiture contained in this Extract againſt <hi>John Swinton,</hi> if the Extract had not been both true and warrantable; and the truth is, the whole particulars that are contained in the ſaid Extract were then recent and freſh in the Memories of a great part of the Members of the Parliament 1661, who had been Members of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee of Eſtates in <hi>anno</hi> 1651, and who had pronounced that Decreet of Forfeiture againſt <hi>Swinton</hi> and others therein contain'd. 2<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. <hi>Swinton</hi> in his Anſwers, Written and Subſcribed by himſelf, given in to the Parliament 1661, therein endeavours to extenuat his Guilt in joyning with the Uſurper <hi>Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well,</hi> and going with him to <hi>Worceſter,</hi> pretending it was becauſe he was out of the Protection of Law, which Words can no otherways be underſtood than of the Decreet and Sentence of Forfeiture pronounced againſt him in <hi>anno</hi> 1651, neither does he in his Anſwers deny that he was Forfeited in <hi>anno</hi> 1651, which is a clear demonſtration of the verity and truth of the foreſaid Decreet. 3<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as it is pretended, that there is no Warrant upon Record of the ſaid Decreet. It is Anſwered, That it is notour and univerſally known, that the Warrants of that year, and of ſeveral other years of the Regiſters, were loſt coming down from <hi>London</hi> in <hi>anno</hi> 1660, and that Extracts furth of the Regiſters make as much Faith as if the Warrants thereof were yet extant, the Lords of Seſſion always ſuſtaining ſuch Extracts out of the Regiſters of theſe years, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſing to grant Certifications againſt any Writs that are Regiſtrat theſe years<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> becauſe the Warrants thereof were loſt in manner foreſaid; and if this Prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive ſhould be ſuſtained or be encouraged to reduce Decreets or Acts of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which are Corroborat by other publick Acts of ſubſequent Parliaments, relative thereto, upon Pretences that the Minuts or Warrants thereof are not extant, then the moſt part of His Majeſties Prerogatives aſſerted by the Acts of Parliament, and all Decreets of Forfeitures, whereupon Annexations to the to the Crown have followed, or Donations to the Liedges may be all called in queſtion and redargued upon the ſame pretences; and therefore the foreſaid Decreet of Forfeiture in <hi>anno</hi> 1651 being unqueſtionably aſtructed as to the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:180098:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
verity thereof by the Parliament 1661, their homologating the ſamine in put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Sentence of Death to execution againſt <hi>Govan</hi> by vertue thereof, and by their ratifying the ſamine in ſo far as concerns <hi>Swinton,</hi> and acknowledged likewiſe by <hi>Swinton</hi> in his Anſwers, the ſame cannot now be redargued upon the pretence of the want of the Records which were loſt in manner foreſaid.</p>
            <p>To the ſecond reaſon of Reduction, bearing, That the King and Committee of Eſtates for reaſons and conſiderations moving them, did reſtrict the Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Puniſhment to the ſaid <hi>John Hume</hi> (who was one of the perſons for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feited in the ſaid Decreet) to the Death, which takes off the effect of the Sentence as to <hi>Swinton</hi> and all the reſt, till it ſhould be reconſidered by the King and Parliament. It is Anſwered, That by this reaſon appears either the groſs ignorance of the Libeller, or his diſingenuity, if not both; for the Doom of Forfeiture is moſt ſolemnly pronounced by ſound of Trumpet, and tearing the Arms of thoſe forfeited, and by reiterat and ingeminat Clauſes forfeiting the Traitors as to Life, Heretage and Movables, which is expreſt and repeated as to <hi>John Swinton,</hi> and the exception is taxative, and relates on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as to <hi>John Hume,</hi> who by the former part of the Doom was forfeited as to Life, Lands, and Heretage alſo, and which is evident by the exception which reſtricts the Sentence as to <hi>John Hume,</hi> that his puniſhment ſhould only be Death when apprehended, and the Eſcheat of his Movables, and the Liferent of his Lands; and both <hi>Swinton</hi> and <hi>Govan</hi> do not ſo much as pretend to, or found upon any reſtriction of that Sentence, when they were brought before the Parliament 1661, which certainly they would not have neglected, if their Reſtriction had been extended to them, and the Decreet and Sentence was conſidered by the Parliament 1661 as not containing any ſuch reſtriction in their favours, when they did not only ordain <hi>Govan</hi> to be execute by vertue thereof, which was accordingly done; but alſo when they did repell <hi>Swinton</hi>'s Anſwers, as being no ways relevant, and did ratifie and approve the foreſaid Decreet, and forfeited him of new for the new additional and ſupervenient Crimes whereof he was Indicted.</p>
            <p>To the third reaſon of Reduction, bearing, That by the late Claim of Right in the Meeting of Eſtates, It is Declared, that the cauſing Purſue and Forfeit perſons upon frivolous and weak Pretences, and upon lame and defective Probation, is contrair to Law, and that the Crimes libelled againſt <hi>John Swinton</hi> were ſuch, being both irrelevant and calumnious.</p>
            <p>It is Anſwered, 1<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. That if the Crimes of Deſerting of the Kings Army by a Commiſſionat Officer, and going in to the common Enemy, who at that time had invaded the Kingdom, and having their reſidence and dayly reſorting and converſing with the ſaid publick Enemy be irrelevant to infer the Crime of Treaſon, then it is not known what can be found relevant to infer that Crime: For 1<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. by Law and the Cuſtom of Nations <hi>de re militari,</hi> who ever accepts a Military Commiſſion or Charge, he cannot at his pleaſure diſmiſs or exauterat himſelf; and <hi>Swinton</hi> having acknowledged, and it being
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:180098:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
proven againſt him that he received his Charge in the Army from the King and Committee of Eſtates, he could not looſe himſelf, or his <hi>cingulum &amp; ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentum militare fine miſſione,</hi> and without his Majeſty and Committee of Eſtates their Licenſe and Warrant; and his pretended giving up of his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, (which in his Anſwers to the Parliament 1661, was by intimating the ſamine to the Chancellor, and to <hi>Gilbert Ker,</hi>) that they received the ſamine off his hands, doth not excuſe, much leſs warrant his withdrawing from his Charge, whereupon the Law, tho he had proceeded no further, put this conſtruction and character of Deſertion, and having gone to the Enemies Quarters <hi>ſine comm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> tu,</hi> Law goes further to put the Character upon him of being <hi>transfuga &amp; hoſtis;</hi> and whatever may be his Pretences of his being ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Priſoner and carried to the Enemies Quarters, where he was ſome time de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained Priſoner, yet they are undoubtedly nothing elſe but Excuſes, to palliat his treaſonable deſigns againſt his King and Country; for if he had not had a deſign to joyn with the Enemy, what could move him to that ſide of the Water and place of the Country where the Enemy was lying, his Family be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on the other ſide, and where he could not Eſcape, being taken by the Enemy; but the true reaſon was, he was afraid that the Treaties and Corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondence which he had with the Enemies before ſhould be diſcovered and he puniſhed for the ſame, and if he had been kept as a Priſoner with the Enemy, is it poſſible that they would have ſuffered him to wear his Sword who had been in Arms againſt them, eſpecially when they had diſarmed all the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men in the Country, and would ſuffer none to wear Swords but thoſe who who were actually in their own Service. And whatever might be Alledged againſt ſimple Converſe, and being preſent with an Enemy, as not relevant to infer the Crime of Treaſon, yet this Converſe being qualified as is Libel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <hi>viz.</hi> the deſerting of his Charge in the Army, his going to the place where the Rebels were, his reſiding and frequent reſorting with them, with his af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Carriage in going in with the Uſurper to <hi>Worceſter,</hi> which he acknowledges in his Anſwers, that he did it at the deſire of the Uſurper; by the Conſtruction of all Law, and by the Laws of this Kingdom is relevant to infer the Crime of Treaſon, and that of the higheſt nature. 2<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. The foreſaid Decreet being ordained by the Parliament to be given out to him to ſee the 15th of <hi>May</hi> 1661, and to give in his Anſwers thereto again that day eight days, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly the ſaid <hi>John Swinton</hi> having gotten up the ſaid Decreet to ſee, he returned the ſamine without any Anſwers, which certainly he would not have done if he had been innocent of theſe Crimes libelled againſt him in the ſaid Decreet, or if the Decreet of Forfeiture had not truly been pronounced againſt him: and ſeing that the Decreet of Forfeiture 1651 is not only ratified by the Parliament 1661 as to <hi>John Swinton,</hi> but thereupon the ſaid Lieutenant <hi>Govan</hi> was excecute as aforeſaid, it is high and bold inſolence in <hi>John Swinton</hi> to have libelled ſuch a reaſon of Reduction, by queſtioning the relevancy of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:180098:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
his Fathers Inditement, which in effect is of no leſs import than to accuſe both the Committee of Eſtates 1651, and the Parliament 1661 of high and mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt Injuſtice, and upon the matter is an impugning of the Authority of the Eſtates and Parliament, which by the Law is declared Treaſon.</p>
            <p>To the fourth Reaſon of Reduction, <hi>viz.</hi> That the foreſaid Decreet is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fective in the Probation, the Decreet neither condeſcending upon the Witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes that were examined againſt him, nor upon what they deponed, but only that the King and Committee of Eſtates have found the Libel relevant and ſufficiently proven, without expreſſing what way the ſame was proven; So that the whole Probation of that Decreet, reſolves in the ſimple aſſertion of one Clerk, without any authentick Document or Probation in record, which in Law is no Probation at all.</p>
            <p>It is anſwered. 1ſt. That the Decreet is opponed, bearing expreſly Sir <hi>Thomas Nicolſon's</hi> compearance, who was then Kings Advocat, before the King and Committee of Eſtates; and deſiring that His Majeſty and the ſaid Committee would conſider the relevancie of the ſaid Libel and Inditement with the Depoſitions of divers famous Witneſſes, Received, Sworn, and examined thereanent: So that the Decreet condeſcends that the manner of Probation was by Witneſſes: And it is neither Practiſe nor Form, to condeſcend upon the Witneſſes names in any Decreets, but only to conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend upon the manner of Probation, whether the ſamine be by Witneſſes, Write, or Oath of Partie. 2ly. After that Sir <hi>Thomas Nicolſon</hi> had deſir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the King and Committee of Eſtates to conſider the relevancie of the Libel, and the Witneſſes Depoſitions; the King and the ſaid Committee did find the Libel as it was raiſed againſt the ſaid <hi>John Swinton. viz.</hi> That he being imployed as Leiutenant-Collonel, and having had the charge of one Troop of Horſe, did deſert the ſaid Charge, and did go in to the Common-Enemy, who had invaded the Kingdom, and did oppreſs the ſame, and had frequent Reſidence with, and did reſort to the ſaid Common Enemy divers and ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral times ſince in the Town of <hi>Edinburgh, Cannongate,</hi> and <hi>Lieth,</hi> relevant to infer the Pain and Puniſhment of High-Treaſon, and found the ſamine pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by the Depoſitions of divers famous Witneſſes, Sworn, Admitted, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined and Deponed, as was clearly known to His Majeſty and the Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee of Eſtates: And therefore, the King and Committee did pronounce the ſentence of Forfeiture againſt him; ſo that it is moſt callumnious to alledge, that the foreſaid Decreet does only bear, that the Libel againſt <hi>Swinton</hi> was found relevant and ſufficiently proven, without expreſſing what way the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine was proven, or that Witneſſes were adduced for proving thereof. And the former Anſwer is repeated, that the Authority of a Parliament is not to be impugn'd, nor are Decreets of Forfeiture to be reduced upon any pretended Nullitie or informality of Proceſs, till firſt the Crime be purged, and the Partie by a Remiſſion be rehabilitat, as is clear by the 135 Act. Parliament 8 King <hi>James</hi> the 6. And as to that part of the foreſaid Reaſon of Reducti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:180098:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>viz.</hi> That there is no authentick Document of the Probation upon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, the ſamine is ſo fully anſwered before, that it is needleſs to repeat it here in this place.</p>
            <p>To the fifth Reaſon of Reduction, <hi>viz.</hi> That the Duke of <hi>Lauderdale,</hi> after he had got an Gift of the ſaid <hi>John Swinton</hi>'s Forfeiture upon the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creet 1651, he did cauſe raiſe a new Indytment before the Parliament 1661, wherein was Libelled the ſame Crime, in the very ſame Words as it was Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belled againſt him in <hi>anno</hi> 1651: And did deſign him <hi>John Swinton</hi> of <hi>Swinton,</hi> which was an implicite paſſing from the ſaid Decreet, and an evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Demonſtration, that it was looked upon by the Duke as no Decreet, it being obvious and clear by Law and Common Senſe; that a man that is once forfeited, cannot be again forfeited, ſeing by the firſt Forfeiture in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of Law, he is no more in being, and can have no Eſtate to forfeit.</p>
            <p>It is anſwered, 1ſt. That this Reaſon hath the ſame Truth in it as the reſt of the Reaſons have, for the Duke of <hi>Lauderdale</hi>'s Gift to <hi>Swinton's</hi> Forfeiture, was not till <hi>May</hi> 1661; And by their own acknowledgment, the Lords of the Articles did upon the ſeventh of <hi>February</hi> 1661, Ordain <hi>Swinton</hi>'s Indyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to be given up to him to ſee and anſwer; And his appearance before the Parliament, was upon the 27 of the ſame Moneth, which was three moneths before the Duke of <hi>Lauderdale</hi> obtained the Gift of <hi>John Swintons</hi> Forfeiture. 2o. Altho <hi>Lauderdale</hi> had cauſed raiſe the Indytment after his obtaining the Gift of Forfeiture, which is moſt calumnious, and had therein deſigned him <hi>John Swinton</hi> of <hi>Swinton,</hi> and had Libelled the ſame Crimes againſt him, which were in the former Decreet 1651. Yet it cannot be inferred either from Law or Reaſon, that it was a paſſing from the former Decreet, for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigning <hi>John Swinton</hi> of <hi>Swinton</hi> is of no moment, that being his ordinary Deſignation, and a wrong Deſignation could neither prejudge the King nor his Donatar, and there is nothing more ordinary, than to deſign Perſons by their former Titles or by their Eſtates which they formerly had right to, whether they had loſt the ſamine by Forfeiture, or had ſold or diſpoſed upon the ſamine. 3ly. Altho the King's Advocat did narrate the ſame Crimes in the new Indytment before the Parliament 1661, for which he was former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly forfeit in <hi>anno</hi> 1651, with ſeveral other new Crimes: As particularly his going in with the Uſurper and Rebells to <hi>Worceſter,</hi> and appearing there in Arms againſt his King and Prince, which was a Guilt and Crime of an higher Nature, than the deſerting of his Majeſties Service; yet it did no ways looſe nor enervate the former Sentence and Decreet, which was ſo juſtly pronounced againſt him in <hi>anno</hi> 1651. And the King's Advocat did not inſiſt againſt the ſaid Deceaſt <hi>John Swinton</hi> upon the Crimes mentioned in the former De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creet to forfeit him a new upon the ſamine, but did inſiſt upon the Decreet 1651; as <hi>Probatio probata,</hi> and that the ſaid Decreet might be ratified and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proven: and accordingly the Parliament did ratifie and approve the ſamine.
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:180098:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
As alſo did of new forfeit him for his being in Arms at <hi>Worceſter</hi> againſt the King, which was the only new additional Article inſiſted upon againſt him, ſo that the firſt Decreet was ſo far from being paſt from, that the ſame was ratified and approven, and the Libelling of the Crimes in the firſt Decreet in the laſt Indytment, was to ſhew a long <hi>ſeries</hi> and continued Tract of the ſaid <hi>John Swinton,</hi> his treaſonable Crimes, and not at all to paſs from the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Decreet: The King's Advocat expreſly deſiring the ſamine to be ratified by the Parliament. 4ly. Altho a forfeited Perſon in the conſtruction of Law, be reputed <hi>nullus et civiliter mortuus,</hi> yet that is only <hi>in odium</hi> of himſelf, and cannot be made uſe of in prejudice of the King, or his Donatar, or any other Perſon; And altho a former Sentence might imped and debar him, from having <hi>Perſonam ſtandi in judicio,</hi> yet it cannot hinder, why he may not be Accuſed, Indyted and Sentenced for Crimes perpetrat be him after the firſt Sentence: And if the laſt Crimes deſerves a greater Puniſhment than the firſt Crimes, for which he was formerly Sentenced, the puniſhment which he was to undergo by the firſt Sentence, may be changed and altered, and the puniſhment decerned in the laſt ſentence, may be inflicted upon him: As for Example, if any Perſon were ſentenced to die as a Murderer, and after his Sentence he ſhould eſcape out of Priſon, and commit the Crime of Treaſon, by the firſt Sentence he is repute <hi>nullus et civiliter mortuus,</hi> and hath not <hi>Perſonam ſtandi in Judicio:</hi> yet it cannot be controverted, but he may be Indyted of new again for Treaſon, and the puniſhment of Treaſon in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted upon him accordingly.</p>
            <p>The firſt Reaſon of Reduction againſt the Decreet of Forfaulture in <hi>anno</hi> 1661. Is in effect an Anſwer to the ſeveral Articles of <hi>John Swinton's</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditement, of which the Earl of Lawderdale does not think himſelf oblidged to take any notice but only in ſo far, as that Reaſon eithe denys, or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenuats the Crime, for which he was of new Forfaulted thereby, <hi>viz:</hi> his going along with the Uſurper in Arms to <hi>Worcester</hi>) the remnant Branches of that Reaſon relating to the other Crimes whereof he was like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe guilty; but were not inſiſted upon againſt him, And therefore are wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by the Earl; tho even as to theſe it is thought very ſtrange how any perſon can have the impudence to aſſert that <hi>John Swinton's</hi> complying with an Uſurper, taking Offices and Places from him, who had invaded his native Countrey with an Army of Sectaries, had murdered his juſt and Lawful So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign, the moſt eminent Perſons, faithfulleſt Subjects, and beſt Patriots of the Kingdom, ſitting in a Pretended Parliament, called by that Uſurper, and Arch-Traitor, where all theſe horrible and deteſtable proceedings were approven; renouncing and abjuring his Native Prince, and declaring his Native King, or any other of the Royal Family not capable to ſucceed in the Royal Government, were not treaſonable Crimes. Therefore to that part of the firſt Reaſon, againſt the third Article of <hi>John Swinton's</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditement,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:180098:9"/>
for which he was now Forfaulted by the Parliament 1661, to wit, his being in Arms at <hi>Worceſter;</hi> and which part of the Reaſon bears, that it was denyed, as it was conceived; and that if it could be made ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear that he was at <hi>Worceſter,</hi> he could have inſtructed, that he was there as a Priſoner; and if he had been in Arms, as he was not; yet this being a Crime alledged to have been committed in <hi>England,</hi> it was remitted by the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Indemnity.</p>
            <p>It is Anſwered, 1. That this is manifeſtly redargued by the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſt <hi>John Swinton</hi>'s anſwers Written and Subſcribed with his own hand, given in to his Inditement in the Parliament 1661. Acknowledging, that he was at <hi>Worcester,</hi> and that he went there at the deſire of the Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per: But for his excuſe, he ſayes, the Uſurper could have commanded him along with him as a Priſoner; but acknowledges, that the Uſurper uſed not that as an Argument with him to perſwade him to go; and that was after he had met with what he then looked upon as hard meaſure from the King and Countrey, being out of the Protection of Law, and that he went i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>  no other Capacitie, but as a Traveler, having no other Arms than Travelers uſe; By which, 1<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. It is proven, that he was perſonally preſent at <hi>Worceſter,</hi> and that he went there at the Uſurpers earneſt intreaties and importunities; which ſhew that there was great intimacie betwixt him and the Uſurper. 2<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. That he hade conceived a prejudice againſt his King and his Countrey by the Sentence of Forfeiture pronounced againſt him in <hi>anno</hi> 1651. which he ſtiles the hard meaſure he met with, and his being out of the protection of the Law. 3<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. That he was there perſonally in Arms, ſuch as a Traveler uſes to ride with, <hi>viz.</hi> Sword and Piſtol, which are all the Arms could be carried by any ſingle Horſe-man there; And altho he denys that he drew either Sword or Piſtol, or did joyn with any Troop or Regiment; yet his being preſent with the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies in Arms, is a ſufficient demonſtration of his joyning with them, againſt his King and Countrey, and is <hi>per ſe</hi> relevant in Law, to infer the Crime of high Treaſon, it being very difficult to prove a mans particular Actings in an Army, who had no remarkable Charge, and his ſerving the Uſurper at that time, is ſufficiently cleared by the rewards that the Uſurper gave him afterwards: And the good Services which are pretended that <hi>Swinton</hi> did to his Countrey-men at that time, is an evident demonſtration of his intimacy and intereſt with the Uſurper; and which could not be done by a priſoner.</p>
            <p n="2">2<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. As to that Alledgance, that the Crime being committed in <hi>England,</hi> it was remitted by the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Indemnity. It is Anſwered, that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Act of Indemnity did extend no further than to the Kings <hi>Engliſh</hi> Subjects, and not to any Subjects who were Scots-men; for as no Law made by the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> could hinder the Parliament of <hi>Scotland</hi> to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed againſt Traitors and Rebels, who were <hi>Scots-men:</hi> ſo no Indemnity paſt in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Parliament could Indemnity a <hi>Scots-man's</hi> Crimes, or could hinder the Parliament of <hi>Scotland</hi> from proceeding againſt them; albeit they had
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:180098:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
been particularly Indemnified by the Parliament of <hi>England.</hi> And all that is now repreſented for <hi>John Swinton,</hi> in this reaſon of Reduction being intirely un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Parliaments conſideration, at the time and by them found relevant and proven to infer the Crime of treaſon; And what is now alledged being then proponed and repelled by the Parliament, cannot now be drawn in que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, And as to which the former Anſwers are repeited.</p>
            <p>To the laſt part of the firſt Reaſon of Reduction inſiſted upon, againſt the ſaid Decreet 1661. <hi>viz.</hi> That the Decreet is lame and defective in its probation? albeit it bears, to proceed upon <hi>John Swintons</hi> Judicial Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, yet there is no ſuch Confeſſion extant in the Records of Parliament, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than what is contained in his Written defence, which are ſo qualified, that it could never be a ground of Forfeiture.</p>
            <p>It is Anſwered, 1<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. That a Judicial Confeſſion emitted before ſo High and Supream a Court as a Parliament, makes full Faith without being Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed; and the aſſertion of the Parliament, and their Act thereupon, is a full and ſufficient Probation: And altho a Judicial Confeſſion emitted before an Inferior Judge, ſuch as Commiſſar or Sheriff, does not make Faith, unleſs it be Signed by the Party; yet a Judicial Confeſſion emitted before the Lords of Seſſion, which is a Supream Court, and ſo marked and Minuted by the Clerk, does make as great Faith, as if it were Subſcribed and Signed by the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: And it cannot be denyed that <hi>John Swinton</hi> compeared before the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and <hi>viva voce</hi> confeſſed theſe horrid and deteſtable Crimes of Treaſon and Rebellion, that he was guilty of, and particularly of his being in Arms at <hi>Worceſter</hi> with the Uſurper, againſt his native King, for which he did blame his Ambition in his younger years, which prompted him to theſe Treaſonable Acts, and as a Remorſe and Abhorrence of them, he ſaid, if they were to do, he would rather with the one hand ſtrike off the other, than be guilty of them; upon which Confeſſion, the King's Advocat took Inſtruments. 2<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. He did not only confeſs the Crimes Libelled and inſiſted on <hi>viva voce,</hi> but in his Anſwers, written and ſubſcribed by himſelf, given in at the ſame time to the Parliament, he did acknowledge the ſame; and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tho in his Anſwers he did endeavour to excuſe and qualifie theſe Crimes, to procure the Commiſeration of the Parliament, that his Life might be ſpared, yet the Parliament did moſt juſtly Repel his Anſwers, and proceeded, and gave Sentence of Forfeiture againſt him, and the excuſes and qualifications adjected, are ſo far from being extenuations of his Crimes, that they rather do aggravat the ſame, being Inſinuations of the great favour, intereſt and intimacy he had with the Uſurper as is evident by the Anſwers themſelves, hereto ſubjoyned; So that the Decreet of Forfeiture, proceeding not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon a verbal Confeſſion emitted <hi>viva voce;</hi> But alſo upon a Written Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, Subſcribed by <hi>John Swinton</hi> himſelf, the ſame cannot now be Invali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:180098:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
or drawn in queſtion, upon the pretence that it is lame and defective in its probation.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Reaſon againſt the Decreet of Forfeiture 1661. is, that the Minuts are Forged and Falſe upon the pretended Grounds following, <hi>viz.</hi> That albeit there be a conſiderable time interveening betwixt the Minuts dated the 7 of <hi>February,</hi> 15 of <hi>May,</hi> and 12 of <hi>July</hi> 1661. Yet it appears by ocular inſpection, that they are all written at one and the ſame time, and with the ſame Pen and Ink, and being compared with the Minuts upon the end of the Inditement, Subſcribed by <hi>Glencairn,</hi> which are the true Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuts, they are much more recent and freſh. 2<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. All the three Minuts, which are on the Margine of the Inditement, being Signatures of the Procedure of the Parliament <hi>in pleno conſeſſu,</hi> the firſt thereof which is on the 7 of <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bruary,</hi> 1661. bears the giving in of the ſaid Inditement againſt the ſaid <hi>John Swinton,</hi> then Pannel, with the former Decreet in <hi>anno</hi> 1651. and craving that the ſaid Decreet might be Ratified, and the new Inditement found Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>levant, and admitted to Probation: The King and the Eſtates of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment are ſaid to ordain <hi>before Anſwer,</hi> the new Inditement to be given up to <hi>John Swinton</hi> to ſee and anſwer; and yet it is evident by the Records of Parliament, that the Articles ſat the 7th of <hi>February,</hi> and not the Parliament, and Ordained the ſame thing that the Parliament Ordained, to wit, The giving up of the Inditement to <hi>John Swinton;</hi> and by <hi>Robert Hamilton's</hi> Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, one of the Senators of the Colledge of Juſtice, and then one of the Clerks of the Parliament: It is evident, that upon the 27 of <hi>February, John Swin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> having formerly received his Inditement, was brought that day to the Bar, and after his Dittay was read, he was appointed that day 15 days, to give in his Legal Defences; (neither was that Term <hi>before Anſwer</hi>) either the ſtile of Parliament, or any Court at that time, being introduced ſince, nor was it at all in this caſe intelligible, it being impoſſible that an Indite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment could be conſidered before it was given up, and ſeen by the party, by which it is clear, as is pretended, that the forſaids Minuts are forged. 3o. The ſecond of the ſaids Minuts being dated the 15 of <hi>May</hi> 1661. appears, as is pretended to be falſe by ocular inſpection, and to have been made up after the year 1670. upon theſe Grounds, <hi>First,</hi> When the Clerk that writes the Minuts, thinking upon the year, wherein the ſaids Minuts were made up by him, which by the Earl of <hi>Crafurd's</hi> Letter appears to have been in the year 1674. he did firſt write the figure 7, and correcting it afterwards, he mends it thus, 6 <hi>Secondly,</hi> By this Minut, dated the 15 of <hi>May, John Swin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> is made compearing, and Judicially confeſſing, that he went with <hi>Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel</hi> and his Army to <hi>Worceſter,</hi> and was with him in that Battle, whereas there was no ſuch Judicial Confeſſion made, and if it had been made, he had certainly Subſcribed it; and <hi>Robert Hamilton's</hi> Diary bears only, That the ſaid 15 of <hi>May John Swinton</hi>'s Dittay, with his Anſwers, were read, and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:180098:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
he alſo heard ſpeak verbally for himſelf, and that the Lord Advocat oppon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Dittay, and produced the former Decreet of Forfeiture againſt him, which <hi>de facto</hi> was never produced till that time, though the firſt Minut falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bear it to be produced upon the 7 of <hi>February;</hi> and which former Decreet the Pannel deſiring to ſee, the Parliament aſſigned him <hi>Friday</hi> come eight days, to ſay what he could ſay, which laſt part of the foreſaid Minut, does alſo bear, That the Pannel was ordained to ſee the foreſaid Sentence of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiture, and to anſwer <hi>Friday</hi> come eight dayes, but with this difference, that the Minut bears upon the Pannel's deſiring to ſee the ſaid Decreet, it was then given up to him, whereas it is evident by <hi>Alexander Reid</hi> his hand, who was Servant to the Lord Advocat, written on the back of the Copy of the ſaid Decreet, delivered to <hi>Swinton,</hi> that it was not given up to <hi>Swinton</hi> to ſee till the 17 of <hi>May;</hi> by which it is evident, that <hi>Swinton</hi> did not make a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny judicial Confeſſion that day, there being no veſtige upon Record, either ſubſcribed by him or the Preſident; and it were abſurd, if he had emitted any judicial Confeſſion, that any further diet ſhould be aſſigned to him to anſwer, ſince <hi>confeſſus pro condemnato habetur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. This Minut of the 15 of <hi>May</hi> 1661. Ordains <hi>Swinton</hi> to ſee and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, as ſaid is<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> againſt the 24 of <hi>May,</hi> and yet neither doth the Decreet bear, That <hi>Swinton</hi> was again called, nor any thing at all of this matter of Fact, that he was ordained to ſee the former Decreet, upon the 15 of <hi>May,</hi> and to anſwer thereunto againſt the 24. which thoſe that framed the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creet did induſtriouſly omit, as forſeeing the inſerting thereof would have inferred a Nullity againſt it, nor was he ever called before the Parliament, that day, or any time thereafter.</p>
            <p n="4">4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. As to the third and laſt Minut, which is upon the 12 of <hi>July</hi> 1661. It is alledged, That the falſhood thereof is manifeſt, in ſo far as 1<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. It makes <hi>Swinton</hi> compearing that day as a Pannel, whereas it is certain he did not compear that day, nor at any time after the 15 of <hi>May.</hi> 2<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. By the ſaid Minut not only the foreſaid pretended Decreet of the Committee of Eſtates 1651. is Ratified, but <hi>Swinton</hi> is declared of new, guilty of the Crime of Treaſon, upon his judicial Confeſſion; and yet there is no ſuch judicial Confeſſion extant, but what was ſo qualified as cleared him. 3. It makes the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Ratifie the ſaid pretended Decreet, without his being heard upon his Defences againſt the ſame, tho a day was aſſigned to him for that effect. 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. The Minut has none of the Solemnities of a Sentence of Forfeiture, not bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Read, Voted, Touched with the Scepter, or any Warrant for publica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by ſound of Trumpet, or Tearing of Arms, and the Signatures of Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences, and Dooms of Forfeiture, after the Voting and Touching thereof, are alwayes written on a paper a part, diſtinct from the Proceſs, and ſigned by the Chancellor, or Preſident of Parliament, which was not obſerved in this caſe.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:180098:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
5<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. All the ſaids three Minuts are ſubſcribed by the late Earl of <hi>Crafurd</hi> as Preſident of the Parliament 1661. with theſe Letters adjected to his Subſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>I. P. D. P.</hi> as if they had been Subſcribed by him in that Parliament <hi>in praeſentia Dominorum Parliamenti,</hi> whereas the Earl's Letter, which a little be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his death, he wrote to the deceaſt <hi>John Swinton,</hi> in the year 1674. diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covers not only that they were not ſigned by him till then, which was 13 years after, but that they were not ſo much as written.</p>
            <p n="6">6<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. After the ſaids Minutes were made up by <hi>Hayſtoun</hi> and <hi>Craufurd</hi>'s Subſcription impetrat thereto, Sir <hi>Archibald Primroſe</hi> the Regiſter, thought himſelf not <hi>in Tuto</hi> to give any Extract thereof under h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> s hand to the Duke of <hi>Lauderdale,</hi> till upon a Petition given in by the Duke to the Lords of Seſſion, bearing, that the ſaid Sir <hi>Archibald</hi> ſcrupled to give any ſuch Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract, which clearly ſhews, the falſneſs of theſe Minutes; And altho he was conſcious to himſelf of the ſame, yet to gratifie the Duke of <hi>Lauderdale,</hi> he prevailed with the Earl of <hi>Craufurd</hi> to ſign them, ſo many Years after the Parliament 1661.</p>
            <p>The Reaſons of Falſhood againſt the Minutes being fully ſet down: It is Anſwered thereto in order as follows, <hi>viz.</hi> To the firſt Reaſon againſt the Minutes, that albeit the ſamine were written at one and the ſame time, yet it imports not, it being notourly known to all Perſons, who are verſant in Buſſineſs, that Clerks do ordinarly write their firſt Minutes upon Papers a part, or Scrolls, &amp; thereafter, or when the affair in Debate is brought to a cloſe, and Decreet pronounced thereintil, they are in Uſe to tranſcribe the Minutes, and ſubjoyn the Interloquitor or Sentence: And it is no Argument, that they appear much more Freſh and Recent than the Minutes Signed by the Earl of <hi>Glencairn</hi> upon the end of the Indytment, to infer from thence, that they were made up long after, for the goodneſs or badneſs of Ink will make Writ ſeem old or new, and ſome Ink will retain its Colour freſh for 20, 30, or 40 Years, Whereas other Ink will loſe its Colour, and appear old in three or four Moneths. But 2ly. The Allegiance is moſt Calumnious, that the Minutes do appear to be Recent, or of the ſame Ink; and altho it did, yet it is Notour, that the writings of a Clerk, who hath one fixed and habitual Character, will look ſo like to his other Writings, though at a different time, that a Man will not be able to diſtinguiſh the difference; But eſpecially, where they uſed to be ſerved and furniſhed with one kind of Ink from one place; which Clerks, who have much Writing, are ordinarly in uſe to do, whereas the Writings of other Perſons not uſed nor habituat with Writing, and with the ſame Ink are eaſily diſtinguiſhable.</p>
            <p>To the 2d Reaſon of Falſhood againſt the firſt Minute, It is Anſwered, That although the Clerk of the Proceſs ſhould have miſtaken, and placed the Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure 7 for 27. yet that cannot infer any nullity in the Minute; for ſuppoſe the day had been left blank, the month and year being condeſcended upon,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:180098:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
doth not render a Minut or any other Paper null; ſo neither can a Clerk's miſtaking, or inſerting one day for another, ſeing the matter of Fact cannot be controverted, <hi>viz.</hi> That <hi>Swinton</hi> did compear before the Parliament upon the 27th of <hi>February,</hi> it being acknowledged by themſelves, and is alſo evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent by <hi>Robert Hamilton</hi>'s Diary; and it is a pitiful Argument to conclude from this miſtake, that the Minutes were forged and made up by <hi>Hayſtoun;</hi> for it <hi>Hayſtoun</hi> or Sir <hi>Archibald Primroſe</hi> had been guilty of forging the Minuts, they would have been much more exact, and would not have given them a Date, which might have been ſo eaſily Canvelled by the Date of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuts Subſcribed by the Earl of <hi>Glencairn</hi> upon the end of the Inditement, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the ſame Date of the Minut in queſtion, which <hi>Hayſtoun</hi> could not but know, he being Clerk to the Proceſs, and having the Grounds and Warrands of the ſame in his cuſtody, which certainly he would have peruſed very exactly, if he had deſigned a Forgery of the Minuts, and could not fall into ſo groſs a miſtake; and it is notour to any, who are verſant in buſineſs, that Clerks, eſpecially in the throng of buſineſs, ſuch as was in the Parliament 1661. do fall in miſtakes of this nature: So that in all this pretended For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery, there being nothing but a quibling on the Date of a Minute, where-through the inadvertence of a Clerk, in the throng of buſineſs, and without any deſign, the Figure 7 is ſet down in place of 27, the ſamine can never a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe to any matter or moment, thereby to redargue a true matter of Fact, <hi>viz.</hi> That <hi>John Swinton</hi> did compear before the Parliament, the 27th of <hi>February,</hi> and that his Inditement was read, and that he gave in Anſwers thereto, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging the Crime; far leſs to overturn a ſolemn Decreet of Parliament. 2<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. As to the Criticiſm upon the words, <hi>Before Anſwer,</hi> that it was not the Style of Courts at that time. It is Anſwered, That it was introduced in Courts long before that time, as may be obſerved in <hi>Durie's</hi> Deciſions; and it was very proper and pertinent to inſert it in the Interloquitor of Parliament, in regard that <hi>John Swinton</hi> having formerly gotten out his Inditement, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to Anſwer the ſamine againſt the 26th of <hi>February:</hi> And having com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared before the Parliament upon the 27th, and the Advocat having inſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed againſt him, and craved, that not only the former Decreet of Forfeiture might be Ratified, but alſo that the new Inditement might be found relevant: The Parliament being reſolved to indulge the Pannel a further day, did not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding of the Advocats deſire, ordain <hi>Swinton</hi> before Anſwer, to ſee the new Inditement, and give his Legal Defences, which was both proper and pertinent. And as to the laſt part of that Reaſon, that theſe words, <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Anſwer,</hi> were not intelligible in that caſe, it being impoſſible that an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditement could be conſidered before it was given up and ſeen by the Party. It is Anſwered, that the ſame is very intelligible, if <hi>John Svvinton</hi> will take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice that the Parliament refuſed upon the Advocats deſire to Ratifie the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Decreet of Forfeiture, which very juſtly they might have done, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:180098:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
allowing him a further time, and might have ordained that Sentence to be put to execution againſt him, as they did to <hi>Govan:</hi> And therefore the words <hi>(Before Anſvver)</hi> ordaining him to give in his Legal Defences, before they would Ratifie the former Sentence, or conſider the relevancy of the new Inditement, were moſt properly adjected, and are very intelligible to any ingenuous or diſ-intereſſed perſon.</p>
            <p>To the third Reaſon of <hi>Falſhood,</hi> being againſt the ſecond Minut, dated the 15th of <hi>May,</hi> 1661. and firſt Branch thereof: It is Anſwered, 1<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. It doth not appear ever to have been the 7th Figure; and there is only a ſtroak of a Pen drawn through the 6th Figure, which might have been done through inadvertency, or a miſtake of the Clerk at the time: And if this pretended Vitiation were compared with the Margent of <hi>Govan</hi>'s Libel, where palpably the Date is Vitiat likewiſe, through miſtake and inadvertancy of the Clerks, that it cannot be determined whether the Date be 13, 18, or 19. Any indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent perſon will eaſily conclude this pretended Vitiation not to be upon de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, or a Forgery: And in effect it is ſo improbable, pitiful, and inconſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent a pretence, that it deſerves not the leaſt Anſwer; and it is not at all Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiat, as it is ſet down in <hi>John Svvinton</hi>'s Paper.</p>
            <p>To the ſecond Branch of that Reaſon concerning <hi>John Svvinton</hi>'s Judicial Confeſſion, it is ſo fully Anſwered in the Anſwer to the laſt part of the firſt Reaſon of Reduction, that it is needleſs here to repeat it. But as to that part of it founded upon <hi>Robert Hamilton</hi>'s Diary, which <hi>John Svvinton</hi> makes uſe of to Canvel the Faith of the former Minut, bearing, That the firſt Decreet of Forfeiture againſt <hi>Svvinton</hi> in <hi>anno</hi> 1651. was produced, and that <hi>Robert Hamilton</hi>'s Diary doth not make mention of any Judicial Confeſſion emitted by <hi>John Swinton</hi> that day. It is Anſwered, That <hi>Robert Hamilton</hi> not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Clerk to the Proceſs, was not obliged to mark ſo fully all that was done, as <hi>Hayſtoun</hi> who was Clerk thereto: And by comparing <hi>Robert Hamilton</hi>'s Diary with the Journals of Parliament, it will be clear and evident, that he did only Minut theſe things that were moſt remarkable in every Affair that came in before the Parliament, and did not Minut ſo fully as thoſe who were Clerks to every particular Proceſs. And <hi>Swinton</hi> having given in his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences and Anſwers to the new Inditement: And likewiſe having Judicially acknowledged his Crime; that which was moſt remarkable that day, was <hi>Swinton</hi>'s compearing, giving in his Defences, and ſpeaking verbally for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; in which words, ſpeaking verbally for himſelf taken notice of by <hi>Robert Hamilton</hi>'s Diary, is certainly included his Judicial Confeſſion, mentioned and taken notice of by <hi>Haystoun</hi> in his Minut: And it is of no weight, that the Minut bears the Decreet of Forfeiture to be given up to him that day; and yet by the Note written by <hi>Alexander Reid</hi>'s Hand, upon the back of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py of the Decreet delivered to <hi>John Swinton,</hi> it appears not to have been gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven up till the 17th of <hi>May</hi> thereafter; For the Clerk might very well have
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:180098:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
marked, that the foreſaid Decreet was given up to him, it being ſo appointed by the Parliament. And although it had not been given up till the 17th day thereafter, it cannot at all derogate from the Faith of the Minuts, and there muſt be more Credit and Faith given to the Minuts of a Clerk, than to any Notes of the Advocats Servant upon the back of the Copy of the Decreet de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered to <hi>Swinton,</hi> which was no part of the Proceſs kept by the Clerk, and might have been put on by the Advocats Servants miſtake or inadvertancy, or might have been a double of the Decreet given to <hi>John Swinton</hi> thereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, when the Principal Decreet was gotten back from him. And as to that pretence, that it was abſurd to aſſign him a further Dyet after a Judicial Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, ſince in Law <hi>Confeſsus pro condemnato habetur.</hi> It is Anſwered, That it was very conſiſtent with the Parliaments Procedure in that Proceſs, becauſe <hi>John Swinton</hi> not only being Indyted upon new Crimes committed by him in <hi>anno</hi> 1651. But likewiſe the Decreet in <hi>anno</hi> 1651. being to be Ratified and Approven, his Judicial Confeſſion being only in relation to theſe new and ſupervenient Crimes, the Parliament might very well aſſign him another day, as they did upon his deſire, to give in his Anſwers to the Decreet 1651.</p>
            <p>To the third Branch of that Reaſon, It is Anſwered, that there was no neceſſity to inſert in the laſt Decreet of Forfeiture, that he had gotten up the former Decreet to ſee, unleſs that <hi>Swinton</hi> had returned the ſamine with par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Anſwers; and although it had been inſert, it would infer no nullity in the Decreet, although <hi>John Svvinton</hi> never appeared before the Parliament thereafter; for having neglected to give in his Anſwers, the Parliament might, and did very warrantably proceed both to Forfeit him upon the new Indite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and to Ratifie and Approve the firſt Decreet.</p>
            <p>To the fourth Reaſon of Reduction being againſt the third and laſt Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nute. It is anſwered, 1<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. That the Minut is opponed, bearing no ſuch thing as <hi>Swinton's</hi> compearance that day, but it doth only bear, that the Parliament having conſidered that member of the new Indytment of Treaſon <hi>pro tempore</hi> inſiſted on with the Pannals anſwer in Write, and <hi>Viva Voce,</hi> and judicial confeſſion, deſire of the Lord Advocat with the former Decreet of Forfeiture, they repelled the ſaids Anſwers given in in Write, and <hi>viva voce</hi> as no ways relevant, and found the formentioned Article and Member of the foreſaid new Indytment inſiſted upon relevant, and proven without mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any mention of the Pannal's Perſonal Compearance. And as to that part of the Reaſon, denying any judicial Confeſſion to be emitted by <hi>Swinton,</hi> or extant in Proceſs, the former Anſwers are opponed. 2<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. Altho there was a day aſſigned to the ſaid <hi>John Swinton,</hi> to give in his Anſwers againſt the firſt Decreet, yet there was no neceſſity to call him before the Parliament thereafter; unleſs he had given in his Anſwers, which he not having done as he was appointed and ordained, the Parliament did very juſtly proceed to pronounce a Sentence of Doom and Forfeiture againſt him upon the new
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:180098:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Indytment, and to ratifie the former Decreet of Forfeiture in <hi>anno</hi> 1651. And the deceaſ'd <hi>John Swinton,</hi> returning the ſaid Decreet without any An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, was a clear and convincing Argument, that he intended to make none againſt the ſaid Decreet, being conſcious to himſelf, that it was juſtly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced againſt him: So that there was no neceſſity to call him when the Parliament adviſed his new Indytment, and pronounced Sentence upon the ſamine, eſpecially conſidering that by the quality adjected to the ſentence, he was recommended by the Parliament to His Majeſty as to his Life. 3<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. As to the laſt part of that Reaſon anent the want of the Solemnities, as Read, Voted, Touched, Warrand for publication by ſound of Trumpet, and tearing of Arms; which certainly would not have been omitted, as is pretended, if any Sentence of Forfeiture had been truly paſt. It is Anſwered, 1<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. That it is admired with what Confidence it can be aſſerted, that there was no Decreet of Forfeiture paſt in that Parliament againſt <hi>John Swinton</hi> in the Year 1661, but that it was made up in the Year 1670, or thereafter, ſeing amongſt the liſt of the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printed Acts of the firſt Seſſion of the Parliament 1661, there is Inſert, not only a Decreet of Forfeiture againſt <hi>John Swinton,</hi> but alſo a Ratification of <hi>John Swintons</hi> Forfeiture, in Favours of the late Duke of <hi>Lauderdale;</hi> And in the Act of indemnity, which was paſt in the ſecond Seſſion of that ſame Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, the Decreet of Forfeiture againſt <hi>John Swinton,</hi> is particularly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted, and by the Decreet of Parliament in <hi>anno</hi> 1661, <hi>John Swinton</hi> being recommended to the King as to his Life, he was ordained to be kept Priſoner in the Caſtle of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> till his Majeſties pleaſure was fully known: So in proſecution of that part of the Decreet upon the ſixteen of <hi>July</hi> 1661, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in four days after the Decreet, the Commiſſioner ſubſcribes a Warrant to the Magiſtrats of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> to deliver the Perſon of <hi>John Swinton</hi> to the Captain of the Caſtle of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> or his Lieutenant, and whereupon <hi>Mercer</hi> Lieutenant of the Caſtle gave his Receipt, which will appear by the Regiſter of the Tolbooth, and Warrants thereof; all which being joyned with the Duke of <hi>Lauderdale</hi>'s Poſſeſſion of <hi>Swinton's</hi> Eſtate, conform to the foreſaid Decreet of Forfeiture, do fully Adminiculat and aſtruct the Verity of the ſaid Doom and Sentence of Forfeiture. 2<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. As to the want of the Solemnities, it is Anſwered, that it is known that Sir <hi>Archibald Primroſe</hi> was a man ſo Exact and Cautious, that he would not have put a Decreet and Sentence of Parliament in the Liſt of the imprinted Acts, nor would he have given an Extract thereof under his hand had not the foreſaid Sentence been both Voted and Read; the hazard thereof, and of forging a Decreet of Parliament, being no leſs, than his Life and Fortune. And it is evident, that the Parliament having conſidered the Proceſs, &amp; having repelled the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences, which were formerly given in, both in Write and <hi>Viva Voce:</hi> And ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving likewiſe conſidered his Confeſſion, formerly mentioned, they behoved to Read and Vote the ſamine, theſe being <hi>ſolemnia ſententiae latae quae ſemper et
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:180098:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
neceſsario ineſse preſumuntur, etiamſi non expreſsa.</hi> And as to the tearing of his Arms and ſounding of the Trumpet, there was no neceſſity thereof, that So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnitie having been performed in the firſt Decreet of Forfeiture in <hi>anno</hi> 1651. And the Touching of Decreets of Forfeitures, is no ways neceſſar, that being only a Solemnitie adhibit to publick Laws, to ſignifie the Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Aſſent, but not at all to Sentences and Decreets betwixt or againſt privat Perſons, except by the Forfeiture, the Lands of the forfeit Perſon be annexed to the Crown: And if any ſuch Solemnity was uſed in any other Decreets of Forfeiture, it was <hi>ex ſuper-abundanti,</hi> there being no ſuch thing required by our Law.</p>
            <p>To the fifth Reaſon of Reduction, being againſt the whole Minutes, It is An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered. 1<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. That <hi>esto</hi> it were true, that the Earl of <hi>Crafurd</hi> did ſign theſe Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutes at the time condeſcended upon in his Letter, yet he does not at all there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in queſtion the Truth of the ſaids Minutes, and of the Sentence of Forfeiture, and <hi>John Swinton's</hi> making uſe of this Letter, to Canvel the Truth of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutes, is the greateſt Imputation and Reflection upon the Honour, Integrity, and Ingenuity of the Deceaſ'd Earl of <hi>Crafurd:</hi> For can any Man in Senſe or Reaſon think, that the Earl of <hi>Crafurd</hi> who was a Man of ſuch Honour and notour Ingenuity, to have had acceſſion to the Signing and Forg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Minutes, which were falſe: And the Earl of <hi>Crafurd</hi> being Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent when the Sentence was paſt, he might very warrantably have Signed the Minutes &amp; Interloquitors, altho never ſo long after, &amp; their not being ſigned till <hi>anno</hi> 1674, as they pretend, is neither a Preſumption, that they were falſe and forged, and made up at that time, nor yet is a nullity upon which the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creet may be drawn in Queſtion: And it is notourly known, that Sir <hi>Archi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bald Primroſe</hi> was a Man of ſuch Integritie, that he would not have had the leaſt acceſſion to ſuch a villanous Action, as forging of Minutes in a Proceſs of Treaſon, which was to ruine a Man both in his Life and Fortune, and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarly would in danger his own. And Sir <hi>Archibald Primroſe,</hi> nor <hi>Haystoun,</hi> were not ſo much oblidged to the late Duke of <hi>Lauderdale,</hi> as could induce them to forge and make up Minutes to gratifie him, neither did <hi>Swinton,</hi> nor any of his Relations while Sir <hi>Archibald Primroſe</hi> or <hi>Haystoun</hi> lived, take up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them the confidence, to alledge that theſe Minutes were Forged or made up by them, but they have fallen upon this Device ſince their Death, thereby to make ſome ſpecious Pretext, to be reponed againſt the Decreets ſo juſtly pronounced againſt the ſaid <hi>John Swinton.</hi> 2<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. The Subſcriptions of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in Office muſt make Faith, otherways there can be no Security nor Certainty to People in their Rights; and where a perſon is <hi>Functus</hi> and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>auterate, it is ridiculous to think, that either his private Letter or Aſſertion ſhould unhinge publick Laws and Sentences, eſpecially ſuch as are founded upon undeniable Evidences, both as to the Relevany and the matter of Fact, otherways it ſhould be in the power of any Preſident of the Parliament, or other Judge at one daſh to defeat and obliterat all the publick Acts and Senten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:180098:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
they have made and paſt in their Office, and this Letter was impetrat by the importunity of <hi>John Swinton</hi> from the Earl of <hi>Crafurd,</hi> and was never made uſe of, nor produced while Sir <hi>Archibald Primroſe</hi> lived. 3<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. Altho the Minuts and Interloquitors had not been ſigned by the Earl of <hi>Crafurd,</hi> yet it is no Nullity, there being no ſpecial Law nor Cuſtom requiring the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine at that time, and the Minuts and Interloquitors of the other Proceſſes of Forfeiture againſt <hi>Guthrie, Govan, Arkindlaſs,</hi> and others in that Parliament, are not ſigned by the Chancellor or Preſident, neither are there any of the Minuts or Decreets of Forfeiture in that Parliament ſo formal as theſe Minuts and Decreet againſt <hi>John Swinton,</hi> which will be evident by inſpection of the Records; and the method and way of managing that Proceſs was adviſed by Sir <hi>John Nisbet</hi> of <hi>Dirltoun,</hi> who was one of the greateſt and eminenteſt Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers and Formaliſts in the Nation; and it can be made appear, by perſons yet living, who were in <hi>Haystouns</hi> Chamber at that time, that this Decreet and Procedure thereof, was made uſe of as an Example in extracting other De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creets of Forfeitures, which were pronounced in that and ſubſequent Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments.</p>
            <p>To the Sixth and laſt Reaſon of Reduction, bearing, that Sir <hi>Archibald Primroſe</hi> did not think himſelf <hi>in tuto</hi> to give Extracts under his hand of the ſaids Minuts, until application was made by the Duke of <hi>Lauderdale</hi> to the Lords. It is Anſwered, That it ſeems the Drawer of the Paper has forgot himſelf, for in the ſtate of his Caſe at the end of the firſt Page, he ſays, that Sir <hi>Archibald Primroſe</hi> did cauſe application to be made to the Lords of Seſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in behalf of the Duke or <hi>Lauderdale,</hi> to give their Warrant for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracting what he was conſcious to himſelf was ſo unwarrantably done; and in this Reaſon he Alledges, that application was immediatly made by the Duke of <hi>Lauderdale</hi> upon Sir <hi>Archibald Primroſe</hi>'s ſcrupling to give out Extracts of the Minuts, which is very inconſiſtent with what he ſays in the ſtate of his Caſe, that application was made by Sir <hi>Archibald Primroſe;</hi> but the truth is, the Duke of <hi>Lauderdale</hi> truly deſired the ſamine might be by Warrant of the Lords, to make the Extract the more authentick, and in caſe that the Minuts ſhould be put out of the way (which the deceaſt <hi>Swinton</hi> neither wanted Cunning nor Art to do, if opportunity offered,) to be an Adminicle for proving and making up the tenor of the Minuts, the late Duke of <hi>Lauderdale</hi> deſired an Extract of the Minuts, and <hi>John Swinton</hi>'s Anſwers alſo, which was the only ground of ſcruple that Sir <hi>Archibald Primroſe</hi> had, becauſe it is not ordinar for Clerks to give the Extracts of Minuts, Interloquitors, or Anſwers, but only of Decreets, and therefore Sir <hi>Archibald Primroſe</hi> as an exact and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Clerk, did ſcruple to give the Extract, either of the Minuts, or of <hi>Swin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi>'s Anſwers, till the Duke of <hi>Lauderdale</hi> made application to the Lords for that effect; and it is ridiculous Nonſenſe, to think that the Lords Warrant to Sir <hi>Archibald Primroſe</hi> for extracting of the Minuts could have made them
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:180098:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
true, if they had been falſe and forged by himſelf, of freed him from the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment due to Forgers; and it is an injurious and calumnious Reflection upon the memory of Sir <hi>Archibald Primroſe,</hi> to alledge that he was conſcious to himſelf of the falſhood of theſe Minuts.</p>
            <p>From all which it is moſt evident and clear, that both the Decreets of Forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture againſt <hi>John Swinton</hi> did proceed upon moſt relevant grounds in Law, and upon moſt legal and full Probation in matter of Fact, and for which (and the other Crimes acknowledged in his Anſwers, but were not inſiſted upon at the time) if he were of new to be indited, he would be again Forfeit by the ſtanding Laws of the Kingdom. And theſe Decreets and Minuts thereof being conſidered, and compared with moſt of all the other Decreets of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiture paſt in that and ſubſequent Parliaments, there will be none found either more relevantly libelled, or ſo formal as to the Minuts, and ſo ſecurely buck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, either as to the Form of Proceſs, or Probation thereof.</p>
            <p>And there is nothing in the printed State of <hi>John Swinton</hi>'s Caſe, and in his pretended Reaſons of Reduction, but what is either Calumnious in matter of Fact, or altogether Irrelevant in point of Law, and are Reflections in the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt degree upon the Honour and Authority of theſe Parliaments; and it is the hight of Boldneſs and Inſolence for <hi>John Swinton</hi> to crave Reduction of his Fathers Forfeiture by way of Juſtice, which is a down-right Accuſing and Taxing of the Parliament and their Sentences with Injuſtice, to which the Sentences of the Lords of Seſſion are not obnoxious or ſubject, and far leſs the Sentences of Parliament, which is the Supreme and Soveraign Court of the Nation: And ſuch a Preparative as this, is of moſt dangerous Conſequence, both as to the Intereſt and Security of His Majeſty and His Subjects; eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſeing by many antient ſtanding Laws and Acts of Parliament, Decreets of Forfeiture are not to be reduced <hi>per modum juſtitiae</hi> upon any pretended nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of Proceſs till the Crime be purged, and that there be a ſpecial Remiſſion of the Crime for which the Forfeiture proceeded; and albeit His Majeſties Bounty cannot be limited to reſtore any perſon by way of Grace, yet by ſuch a Reſtitution, neither His Majeſties Donatar, nor the Intereſt of any third Party is prejudged; and it was upon theſe Conſiderations, that all the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Commiſſions that were appointed to make Enquiry into this Forfeiture came to no Iſſue, and were rendred ineffectual.</p>
            <p>In reſpect whereof, the Earl of <hi>Lauderdale</hi> ought to be Aſſoilzied from the ſaid pretended Reaſons of Reduction.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:180098:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Follows the Names of theſe who were appointed in <hi>anno</hi> 1682, by a Commiſſion under the Great Seal to take Tryal and Enquiry anent the deceaſt <hi>John Swinton</hi>'s Forfeiture.

<list>
                  <item>Sir <hi>George Gordon</hi> of <hi>Haddo,</hi> Chancellor.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>William</hi> Marqueſs of <hi>Queenſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berry,</hi> Theſaurer.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>John</hi> Marqueſs of <hi>Athol,</hi> Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy Seal.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>James</hi> Earl of <hi>Perth,</hi> Juſtice General.</item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>David Falconer,</hi> Preſident of the Seſſion.</item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>George M<hi rend="sup">c</hi>kenzie</hi> of <hi>Tarbat,</hi> Clerk Regiſter.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>John Drummond</hi> of <hi>Lundin,</hi> Theſaurer Deput.</item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>George Mackenzie</hi> of <hi>Roſehaugh,</hi> Lo. Advocat.</item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>John Lockhart</hi> of <hi>Caſtlehill,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>and Sir <hi>John Murray</hi> of <hi>Drumcairn,</hi> Senators of the Colledge of Juſtice.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:180098:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>John Swinton's</hi> Anſwers to his Inditement, given in to the Parliament, <hi>1661.</hi> written &amp; ſubſcribed with his own hand.</head>
            <p>ANSWERS by way of Defence, for <hi>John Svvinton</hi> of <hi>Svvinton,</hi> to the Inditement of Treaſon, whereof he ſtands accuſed by the King's Advocat, at the inſtance of the King, before the King's Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioner and Parliament, adhering to what was offered by him to the Commiſſioner, the 27th of the laſt Moneth, by way of Information, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſting, that if need be is, according to the then grant of the Commiſſioner and Parliament, (intimat by the Chancellor as Preſident) he may be further heard to ſpeak in their preſence, by way of Information, or otherways; in obedience to their Command, he (having liberty and allowance from the Lords) doth ſingly and plainly anſwer by way of Defence in Write; Thus, waving all dilator Defenſes, even ſuch as the Law allows him, either as to what might be ſaid to the Informlaity of the Proceſs, or to what he might ſay why he ought to be left to the common proceedings in Law, before the Court ordinary to be Tryed, by the known Laws of this Nation, which is the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Benefit and Security of every Subject to plead, ſpecially in this time of peace and ſettlement; As alſo waving what he might have to ſay in that known Maxim of <hi>Socii criminis.</hi> And even this way of pleading by Writ, and ſeverals of that kind, he doth with his own conſent, without diſputing, homologat the Juriſdiction of the Court of Parliament, not ſo much as ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting againſt any one from being his Judge in this matter, being willing it ſhould receive a plain and clear iſſue, even in this way, being about to give his Anſwer to this Court, thus conſtitute of the Repreſentatives of King and people, whatever may be the debateable Conſideration, how far the King or people diſtinctly conſidered, are ſubject to, or above the Law: Yet here taking them Collectively, there is more to be ſaid for theſe proceedings, that run not ſo properly in the Channel of Law, ſpecially if the Parliament being thus Conſtitute in theſe Tryals, ſhall proceed not only by vertue of their Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecutive Power, but alſo of their Legiſlative: And as this ſtates a vaſt illi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited power, (as it were in the Parliament) So it calls upon all and every one of them, in the dread of the Living God, to conſider what they do in theſe things, that they judge not for men, but for the Lord, who is indeed Supream; and therefore as he declines not the Law of his Native Countrey, but may in his ſubſequent Anſwers, ſay ſomewhat to that, why he ought to be Aſſoilzied, and acquitted from the Inditement: Yet being to anſwer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a Court, that (it is like) will not look upon themſelves as ſo ſtrictly tyed to the Letter of Laws, as the extraordinary Courts of Juſtice muſt be,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:180098:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
as having a large and mixed power comprehenſive of Law, Equity and Reaſon, and it may be reaſon of State too, ſo to ſpeak; and a power incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trollable, to execute their Determinations, whether <hi>de jure,</hi> or not, he ſhall leave to the judgment of that in every one of their Conſciences, wherein as they weigh and conſider it in the coolneſs of their minds, they will owne that <hi>de jure</hi> it is Supream; The higher power <hi>to which every knee muſt bow,</hi> and ought to be ſubject to, <hi>in heaven and earth;</hi> to which the King and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple muſt give an account, even the light of Chriſt in every of their Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, the Law written in their hearts; the Faithful Witneſs for God, that diſcovers to man his Thoughts, that brings him many times after his firſt ſleep to conſider what ſhall be the end of Pride, Luſt and Vanity, that which oppreſſeth this Juſt Witneſs, which is the Foundation of Society of all juſt Laws, the <hi>vinculum</hi> that tyes man to God, and one to another, even that which leads to the Love of God, and to love our Neighbour as our ſelves, and ſtabliſheth that grand Principle of Juſtice, to do as one would be done by, is the Foundation of all juſt Magiſtracy, is the Line and Rule of true Judgment, proper to be minded and headed, and turned to by the Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioner and Parliament, and every Member of it. To this Rule, Law and Judge, the Defender ſubmits and appeals in this matter, even the Light and Witneſs for God in their Conſciences: And as to what he ſhall offer to them of the Law of this Nation, (which is or ought to be Founded on this) Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty or Reaſon, he ſhall leave it to this Witneſs near them, and in their hearts, the Eternal and Ingrafted Word, Chriſt the Light, that enlightens every man that is come into the World; To this he ſhall leave it, as the laſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal, and let him ſtand Juſtified or Condemned, according as the Judgment ſhall be given in this Law, which is only in this caſe, (and as they are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted) capable to bind a Parliament, who may, it is like, look upon themſelves as to men, and Letter of Laws as Supream, which he doth not think unproper or unſerviceable for the Parliaments Conſideration, to be thus offered <hi>in limine,</hi> which they will find of the greater neceſſity and uſe for them, to mind upon the account of the King's Honour and Safety, the Nations and their Own, the Foundations of all Laws, (outward) Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Magiſtracy having been ſo perplexed and involved, intrinched upon, brangled, ſhattered, and a general Conſternation; The minds of men by reaſon of theſe things, much eſtranged, engaged in Animoſities and Facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and that through their departing from this juſt Law, and principle in themſelves; So that is impoſſible for them, going by another Rule than this, as the Supreme, to be guided in a ſafe and healing Path, ſo as they may be a Bleſſing to themſelves, and the people over which they are, and have comfort in their Work when they have done; This is his Advocat in all their Conſciences, and to this he ſhall commit what he hath to ſay by way of Defence, here to ſtand or fall, to be cleared, acquitted, or condemned,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:180098:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
having a place in the Light and power of God, to receive whatever ſhall be the iſſue of this matter, as from his own hand, not minding man nor men, layed down at quiet in his will, ſtanding in that which is out of the fear of man, in the fear and dread of the living God.</p>
            <p>And ſo to proceed to his Anſwers, The Defender denys the Inditement, as it is conceived: As to the firſt part of the firſt Article of the Inditement, (paſſing the general part of it, and the Acts of Parliament therein mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſome of them being only Statutory, none of them meeting the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars Charged againſt the Defender, or any one of them ſtrickly taken, as all Laws are to be in this caſe eſpecially, and where the Purſuer ſhews, how in particular way of application, they do, and doth condeſcend, it may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive a particular Anſwer) The Defender doth deny this Article, and all of them as they are conceived; Yet doth not deny but that he ſat in the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament 1649. Whether he did Vote to the Reſcinding of that Act of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament 1648. relating to the Ingagement, he doth ſingly declare, That he doth not remember, neither can he ſay how far he Voted, or conſented to the putting out of any Officer of State, Judges or others, their places, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing elſe, particularly Charged in this Article, the thing is ſo long ago; but ſuppoſing it were clearly proved that he was a Voter in both theſe, or in any thing elſe Charged againſt him, as acted by him as a Member of that Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, <hi>affirmativè;</hi> It is offered by way of Defence, That he came and ſat in that Parliament by a Commiſſion from his Countrey, and they were not only owned by the Nation as a Parliament for the time, but alſo by the King in that capacity, he receiving Commiſſioners from them as the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Nation, Treating with Him as ſuch, a Treaty concluded, one of the Articles of which was a Ratifying of that Parliament, and their proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, with an engagement to compleat it in a more formal way, at his home coming, which was done by an Act of  <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap>  of  <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap>  of  <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap>  date, particularly by the King and Parliament: Much might be ſaid upon other Mediums, but this is ſo ſtrong, ſo full and clear, to Aſſoilzie the Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der from that part of the Libel, as it may ſuffice.</p>
            <p>As to the other Branch of the firſt Article of the Inditement, wherein the Defender is Charged with ſeveral other particulars, as his Voting to, and carrying on the Murther of <hi>Montroſe, Huntly,</hi> and others; and all theſe Charged upon him, as he was a Member of the Parliament 1649. It not being remembred, That what was done in moſt, if not in all theſe particulars, was done by that Parliament, that ſat in the month called <hi>March,</hi> One thouſand ſix hundred and fifty, which (whatever elſe might be pleaded to warrand its Inditement,) was the time appointed by the Act of Parliament of  <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap>  1648, conform to the Act of Parliament  <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap>  for conſtituting Triennial Parliaments; ſo his Defenſe to that part of the Charge is, (repeating alſo here that part of his Defenſe to the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:180098:17"/>
former, the Treaty, and the Act of Ratification paſt by the King and Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,) that he as he came there by vertue of a Commiſſion from his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, ſo he came to a Parliament that ſtood upon a more unqueſtioned Foot in Law, and in theſe particulars, he is not, nor cannot be charged as acting any other ways than in the Capacity as he was a Member of Parliament; and by way of Information, he hath ſaid ſomewhat towards clearing himſelf from the <hi>Odium</hi> that hath been caſt upon him in theſe things, and might ſay more, and may if there be opportunity, yet this ſhall ſuffice by way of Defenſe. To the ſecond Article of the Defenders Charge, as to the firſt part of it, he doth ſimply deny it, and admits it of conſent relevant to be proven, and tho he ſhould be acquitted of this Inditement upon this Tryal, he doth hereby conſent and declare, that if ever hereafter it can be made appear, that he was Guilty of betraying his Truſt, let the concluſion of the Inditement take place againſt him, or the worſt of Puniſhments can be deviſed. As to the ſecond Branch of the ſecond Article of his Charge, he doth deny it as it is conceived, tho he doth not deny but as he received his Charge from the Committee of States, he did to the then Chancellor in the Committee-Room at <hi>Stirling,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare his laying down of his Charge, deſiring him to intimat the ſame to the Committee, and at the ſame time did intimat the ſame to Collonel <hi>Gilbert Ker</hi> his immediat ſuperior Officer, and forthwith <hi>Crafurdland</hi> was put into his place: This he thinks he is able to prove <hi>inſtanter</hi> (if need beis,) as alſo before ever he went to that part of the Country where his Eſtate lay, and where his Buſineſs called him, he was upon the place where Collonel <hi>Ker</hi>'s Regiment was, where he actually did ſee the foreſaid <hi>Crafurdland</hi> in his Charge, he being occaſionally there for clearing ſome things with his Officers, and others relating to his former Charge, this was not under ſome Weeks (if not Months) after he had layed down his Charge, and the other in the poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of it, ſo that it can never be ſaid with any colour that he deſerted his Charge, as the word is commonly received and accepted, and as the import of it is in this place of the Charge. It is alſo true, that his Occaſions leading him towards <hi>Berwick</hi>-ſhire, where the only Eſtate he had lay, he was Seaſed upon and made Priſoner by a Party of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> carried to their Generals Quarters, and having given an account to him of his Occaſions in theſe parts, he did declare to him, that tho he was his Priſoner, yet he ſhould have liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty upon his Parol (or ſo) to go to his Lodging and about his Affairs. That he was taken Priſoner and thus brought in, he offers him to prove (if need be,) and tho through the General's Permiſſion he had liberty to go into the Country with his Family, and as the neceſſity of his own Affairs or the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys did require (whoſe Condition then was much diſtracted and oppreſſed) He came to <hi>Edinburgh</hi> ſometimes, he having a ready acceſs to the General, through the forementioned opportunity, and he forward enough to oblige him, which he can truely and ſingly ſay, that (according as the State he was
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:180098:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
then in could admit) he laid him out to the outmoſt for preſerving of that part of the Country and every individual in it, as he had acceſs and opportunity; and if this can be called joyning with the Enemy, as this Caſe is circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiated, or that by any Law of God or Man it can ever be charged upon him as a Guilt ſpecially to infer the concluſion of the Inditement, let all ſober Men judge. To the third Article of the Inditement, he doth deny it as it is conceived, tho it is true that he was at <hi>Worceſter,</hi> and as he was there, it is alſo true he went thither through the earneſt Intreaties and Importunities of him, that (though he doth ingenuouſly declare, that he cannot ſay that he did uſe that as an Argument) could have commanded him along with him as his Priſoner, and whoſe Priſoner he was upon the matter, and this after he had then met with that he then looked upon as hard meaſure from the King and Country out of the protection of Law, theſe temptations he was under, and yet he went in no other Capacity than as a Traveller, no other Arms than a Traveller; and if it ſhall be made our that ever he joyned ſo much as in any Troop, or carried any Charge, or that in any occaſion there, the Battel or otherways, he did draw his Sword or looſe a Piſtol, he admits all or every one of theſe rele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant of conſent to infer the concluſion of the Inditement. It is known how greatly uſeful his there being was to his Country-men, not only of his neareſt Relations whom he found deadly wounded, but many others, the particulars whereof needs not to be mentioned, he having indeed a ſufficient reward in the work it ſelf, doing it upon a free and ſingle intention, never thinking of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king uſe of it upon ſuch an occaſion as this. Only this he can ſay in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the ſearcher of hearts, that he thinks if the Parliament ſhould find the Inditement againſt him upon that ſingle Head of being at <hi>Worceſter,</hi> as he doth look upon that as Principal, and all the reſt but Acceſſories (as it were) even in the intention of the Libeller, the Sentence paſt as to Life and Eſtate, and it ready to receive its laſt Conſummation, he could receive it, and ly down under it with a more chearful heart, than he enjoyed any time he was at <hi>Worcester,</hi> to ſee and be Witneſs of the reproach of his Countrey, and the diſtreſs his Countrey-men was under. His Defence is, that it was in <hi>England</hi> the Crime, what-ever it was, was committed where it is properly try able, and where the King (in whoſe Name, and by whoſe Advocat this Inditement is proſecute) hath Indemnified the Defender from it; And that he hath ſo done, will appear by the expreſs words of the 5th Clauſe of the Act of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnity. And tho it may be Objected that this is an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Law; It is ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced in the caſe of Crime committed in <hi>England,</hi> tryable in <hi>England,</hi> par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donable in <hi>England,</hi> pardoned in <hi>England,</hi> and that by him againſt whom the offence was committed, what-ever it was, the Defender actually a Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner in <hi>England,</hi> and from thence ſent hither a Priſoner, brought hither in an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Frigot; ſo that as to this Crime, in this caſe, as it is circumſtantiated, it is pleadable, and by the Defender Pleaded as his Defence. And this is
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:180098:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
mainly to be minded in this particular of the Inditement, That the Defender (when he could have ſhunned it) was taken in <hi>England,</hi> was kept 19 Weeks and upwards cloſs Priſoner there; was ſent from <hi>England</hi> hither by the King's Authority, to receive a Tryal in his own Countrey, for ſuch things as he is chargeable with at the inſtance of the King, as acted here in his own Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey. For it can never be underſtood, that the King in Honour, Juſtice, or Equity, would ſend him down out of <hi>England,</hi> to be tryed for his Life and Eſtate here, for a Crime committed ſo many years ago in <hi>England,</hi> and which he hath abſolutely and freely Remitted there, as fully, as if the Defenders Name and Sirname were particularly expreſt, as Indemnified, and that par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Act of his being at <hi>Worceſter,</hi> expreſly remitted; by reaſon whereof he ought to be Aſſoilzied from this Article of the Inditement. As to the 4th Article of the Inditement, It is denyed, as it is conceived, tho he doth not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny but he was in a Parliament of <hi>England</hi> by a Call and Commiſſion from his Countrey, the Nation having ſo far ſubmitted to the Union with <hi>England,</hi> that they ſent their Deputies to ſeveral Parliaments. By what Law this is Crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal (ſpecially as it is circumſtantiated) when the Purſuer ſhews, it may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive an Anſwer. To the other Branch of the Article, The Defender doth ingeniouſly declare, he doth not remember that he was at any ſuch Vote of renouncing the King and his Family, neither doth he think he was; however, if he was, it was in <hi>England:</hi> And if it ſhould be proven, as he is confident it will never be, he repeats his Defence adduced in the Caſe of <hi>Worceſter.</hi> To that Branch of the Article, His receiving Imployments from <hi>Oliver Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel</hi> and others, as one of the Commiſſioners for Adminiſtration of Juſtice, and one of the Council: That part of the Article is ſo far confeſt by him, that he was in theſe Imployments, but never in theſe, nor in any, till his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey Nationally had ſubmitted (ſtopping for the good of the Nation to the neceſſity of the time) to the Authority of <hi>England.</hi> And as things were then ſtated, he doth believe, it was look'd upon by the Nation as for the good and ſervice of the Countrey, that Countrey-men were admitted to, and did act in theſe Imployments; and that it was look'd upon as no diſ-ſervice or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advantage to his Countrey at that time, that the Defender was one: And he can truly ſay, that the ſervice of his Country was none of the leaſt induce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, to engage him in the accepting of, and continuing to theſe Imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. And if ever it can be made appear, that he ſought after one or ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of them, let it infer the Concluſion of the Summons, as relevant of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent. What the tendency of his way in theſe Imployments was, towards the ſervice or diſ-ſervice of his Countrey, let his greateſt Enemy Witneſs in this day, he ſhall not in theſe things bear Witneſs for himſelf; the more narrowly, and particularly his way in theſe things ſhall be inquired into, it ſhall be the leſs diſadvantage to him. And as to the inſinuations of the great profits and advantage he hath had, he ſhall only give it this Anſwer, which is ſingle truth,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:180098:18"/>
that notwithſtanding what-ever he received one way or another, he can ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly declare, and doth, that tho he were not chargeable by the King, nor any other, as to his Eſtate, or any Charge relating thereto, upon the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of his acting in theſe things, but were cleared of all theſe, he is two thouſand Pounds <hi>Sterling</hi> and upwards more in debt than he was left by his Father, when be died in the year 52. occaſioned through his Expences in tumbling about in theſe matters: This he mentions only upon this occaſion, that it may appear he hath not enriched himſelf in theſe times, but indeed even in that way half endangered the deſtroying of that Eſtate conveyed to him by his Anceſtors. And now having given theſe plain Defences to the Articles of the Inditement, wherein he hath endeavoured to contract much of what might be ſaid, not only by way of Information, but alſo by way of Defence <hi>pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remptorie,</hi> being purpoſely omitted; tho they may be look'd upon as ſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal (as it may be judged) need were, yet let them be weighed in the juſt Ballance, the eternal Rule of Righteouſneſs, and the Defender doubts not, but by that Law which is Supream, the Law of this Nation, the Law of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Equity and Reaſon; nay, admitting Reaſon of State alſo in its place, to have its own weight, as this matter now ſtands before the Parliament, and is circumſtantiated, it being remembred by the Commiſſioner and Parliament, that it was not early the Defender became engaged in the Publick Tranſaction of theſe times, as is manifeſt by the Inditement it ſelf, the Parliament in Juſtice will find the Anſwers relevant, to elide the Inditement, and to Aſſoilzie the Defender.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Sic Subſcribitur</hi> J. Swinton. </signed>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Extractum de Libro Actorum, per me</hi> A. Primeroſe<hi>Cls. Reg.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="minutes">
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:180098:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Minuts of <hi>John Swinton</hi>'s Proceſs of Forfeiture in <hi>anno 1661.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>EDinburgh</hi> 7 <hi>February.</hi> 1661. Sir <hi>John Fletcher</hi> His Majeſties Advo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat, having given in, and repeated in preſence of the Parliament, the Libel and Inditement purſued by him for His Highneſs Intereſt, againſt <hi>John Swinton,</hi> Pannal: Together alſo with the Decreet of Forfeiture pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced by the Committee of Eſtates, as having Power by Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for that Effect againſt the ſaid Pannal, Dated at <hi>Ferth</hi> the ſecond day of <hi>April</hi> 1651. He craved that the ſaid Decreet of Forfeiture might be ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified, and approven by the Eſtates of Parliament, and Ordained to be put to Execution. And without Prejudice thereof, Further craved, that the ſaid new Inditement might be found Relevant and admitted to his Probation. The Kings Majeſty, and Eſtates of Parliament before Anſwer, ordains the new Inditement to be given up to the ſaid <hi>John Swinton,</hi> Pannal: He being in Priſon within the Tolbooth of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> to the Effect, he may ſee the ſamine,, and anſwer thereto 15 <hi>May</hi> 1661. The Pannal having ſeen the ſaid new Inditement, and given in Anſwers and Objections there againſt Extant lying in Proceſs; And who being Perſonally preſent, and heard ſpeak for himſelf <hi>Viva Voce</hi> in open and plain Parliament, did judicially Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs and Acknowledge, That he went in Company with <hi>Oliver Cromwel,</hi> with that Armie to <hi>Worceſter,</hi> and was with that Army at the Battel of <hi>Worceſter:</hi> Whereupon His Majeſties Advocat asked Inſtruments, and declared, that he inſiſted allannerlie <hi>pro tempore</hi> upon that part of the ſaid new Libel, bearing that the Pannal did go along with the ſaid Uſurper, In Arms in the Army of <hi>Sectaries</hi> libelled: and was actually at <hi>Worceſter,</hi> upon the 3d of <hi>Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember</hi> 1651 years, and did Fight in Hoſtile manner againſt his Majeſty and Army of <hi>Scotsmen,</hi> at the leaſt was with the ſaid Uſurper, with his ſaid Army of <hi>Sectaries</hi> in Arms as ſaid is, and that he Treaſonably Aſſiſted, Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanced and promoted all the ſaid Uſurper his wicked and treaſonable Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes and Deſigns; Likeas the ſaid Lord Advocat repeated his former Deſires, and not only craved, that the ſaid Decreet of Forfeiture might be approven, and ordained to be put to Execution: But likeways, that the Pannal may be again found and declared to be guilty of the Crime and Lyable to the Pain and Puniſhment of Treaſon: And to be Decern'd and ordain'd to underly the ſamine. The Pannal craved to ſee the former Sentence of Forfeiture, which was given up to him to ſee and give in his Anſwers upon <hi>Friday</hi> come
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:180098:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
eight days, being the 24 of <hi>May</hi> inſtant; &amp; to alledge why the ſamine ſhould not be put to Execution, with certification <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 12 <hi>July</hi> 1661. His Majeſty and Eſtates of Parliament, having conſidered that Member of the new In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditement of Treaſon <hi>pro tempore</hi> inſiſted upon, with the Pannal's Anſwer in Writ, and <hi>Viva Voce,</hi> and Judicial Confeſſion and Declaration, deſire of the Lord Advocat, with the former Decreet of Forfeiture. They re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled, and repells the ſaids Anſwers and Objections made &amp; given in in Writ, and <hi>Viva Voce</hi> as no ways Relevant, &amp; finds the forementioned Article &amp; Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the ſaid new Inditement inſiſted upon, relevant and proven by the ſaid Pannal his judicial Confeſſion; And therefore not only ratifies and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proves the former Decreet of Forfeiture againſt the ſaid <hi>John Swinton,</hi> Pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, but alſo of new finds and declares, that the ſaid Pannal is guilty of the ſaid Crime of Treaſon; And has incurred the ſaid Pain and Puniſhment of High Treaſon <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And recommends to the Kings Majeſty his conſideration, the putting the Sentence and Decreet to Execution againſt the ſaid Pannal, In ſo far as concerns his Life allannerlie, and ordains the Perſon of the ſaid Pannal to be keeped in Priſon within the Caſtle of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> till His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties pleaſure be further known thereanent.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Sic ſubſcribitur</hi> Crafurd Lindſay, <hi>I. P. D. Parl.</hi>
               </signed> 
               <signed>
                  <hi>Extractum de libro Actorum per me.</hi> A. Primroſe, <hi>Cls. Reg.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:180098:20"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
